<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Apanthismata. memorials of worthy persons lights and ornaments of the Church of England, two new decads.</title>
            <title>Memorials of worthy persons. Decades 1-2</title>
            <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B790A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172266</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369023</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">187791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08424)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2842:19a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Apanthismata. memorials of worthy persons lights and ornaments of the Church of England, two new decads.</title>
                  <title>Memorials of worthy persons. Decades 1-2</title>
                  <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 104, [8], 135 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. and L. Lichfield and are to be sold by S. Thomson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed with Wing B802: Memorials of worthy persons (lights and ornaments of the Church of England.) the fourth decad. / by Cl. Barksdale. Oxford : Printed by A. and L. Lichfield, 1663.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Apanthiſmata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MEMORIALS OF Worthy PERSONS Lights and Ornaments OF THE <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two new Decads.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnia, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nihil.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>S. Thomſon</hi> at the Biſhops-head in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:2"/>
            <p>Nobiliſſimo Adoleſcenti, D. <hi>EDVARDO HYDE,</hi> Ex Aede Ch.</p>
            <p>Illuſtriſſimi Viri <hi>EDVARDI</hi> Comitis de CLARENDON, Regni ANGLIAE &amp; Acad. OXONIENSIS CANCELLARII Honoratiſſimi, Filio non degeneri: <hi>C. B.</hi> Ejuſdem <hi>Cancellarii</hi> benignitate Rector de <hi>Naunton</hi> in Agro <hi>Gloc.</hi> Libellum ſuum, Animi non immemoris indicem, Humillime D. D.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Magni propago Seminis, Collegii</l>
               <l>Henriciani, Matris ac almae decus,</l>
               <l>A Matre poſſes ſumere exemplum Tibi,</l>
               <l>Niſi eſſet inſtar omnium Clarus Pater.</l>
               <l>Haec noſtra non erunt inutilia tamen:</l>
               <l>Sunt iſta fortiora quae plures docent.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:3"/>
            <head>The Perſons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>K.</hi> Edward 6.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>La.</hi> Jane Grey.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Sir</hi> John Cheek.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Arch B.</hi> Whitgift.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Mr.</hi> Rich. Hooker.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrews.</item>
               <item>7. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Brounrig.</item>
               <item>8. <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Gataker.</item>
               <item>9. <hi>Dr.</hi> H. Hammond.</item>
               <item>10. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Smith.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_his_book">
            <head>Ad Librum.</head>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ade, Liber, pede felici: Lectoribus eſto Delicium, tantis auree Nominibus</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:4"/>
            <head>To the Ingenuous Readers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe <hi>Perſons</hi> here preſented, are worthy, certainly, of an <hi>honourable</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: the <hi>particulars</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected are ſuch as, to me, ſeemed moſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable.</hi> More you may find, if you deſire, in the <hi>Authours</hi> to whom I refer you: For I would be taken only for a faithful <hi>Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</hi> The <hi>benefit</hi> to be received hence (which I do principally aim at) is, that you may worthily eſteem of our <hi>Church,</hi> adorned with ſuch excellent <hi>examples;</hi> and that, by your <hi>imitation</hi> of theſe, <hi>your ſelves</hi> may deſerve to be, hereafter, added to the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Servant, C. B.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Oxon.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Apr.</hi> 23. <hi>Die Coron. R. Car.</hi> 2. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>EDOUARD VI.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:187791:5"/>
            <head>MEMORIALS. I. K. <hi>EDWARD</hi> VI.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of Dr</hi> Heylyns <hi>Hiſtory of the Reformation,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Dward,</hi> the only ſurviving Son of K. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. was born at the Royal Palace of <hi>Hampton Court, Oct.</hi> 12. 1537. of Q. <hi>Jane Seymour</hi> the next wife to K. <hi>Henry</hi> after <hi>Anne Bollen.</hi> Some Ladies who had ſeen the Pictures of both Queens at <hi>Whitehal</hi> Gallery, have entertained no ſmall diſpute to which of the two they were to give preeminence in point of beauty; each of them having ſuch a plentiful meaſure of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to entitle either of them to a ſuperiority. If Q. <hi>Anne</hi> ſeemed to have the more lively coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, Q. <hi>Jane</hi> was thought to carry it in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:187791:6"/> exact ſymmetry, which ſhewed it ſelf in all her features. Love which ſeemed to threaten in the eyes of Q. <hi>Jane,</hi> did only ſeem to ſport it ſelf in the eyes of Q. <hi>Anne.</hi> There was more Majeſty in the garb of Q. <hi>Jane Seymour,</hi> and more lovely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in that of Q. <hi>Anne Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en:</hi> yet ſo, that the Majeſty of the one did excel in lovelineſſe, and that the lovelineſſe of the other did excel in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. In a word, Q. <hi>Jane</hi> had in her all the Graces of Q. <hi>Anne,</hi> but governed with an evener and more conſtant temper.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It hath been commonly reported and no leſs generally believed, that the child being come unto the birth, and there wanting natural ſtrength to be delivered, his Mothers belly was ripped open to give him a paſſage into the world. But there are extant two ſeveral letters to evince the contrary. Though queſtionleſſe, ſhe had a very hard labour, which brought her firſt into a very high diſtemper, and after into a very great looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which accelerated the approach of death, to the General lamentation, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="epitaph">
               <body>
                  <head>Her Epitaph.</head>
                  <p>Phoenix Jana jacet, nato Phoenice. Dolendum eſt, Secula Phoenices nulla tuliſſe duas.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p n="3">3. The Prince having attained unto the age of ſix years was taken out of the hands of his women, and committed to the Tuition of Mr <hi>John Cheek</hi> (whom he afterwards Knighted, and advanced
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:187791:6"/> him to the Provoſt-ſhip of Kings Coll. in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge)</hi> and Dr <hi>Richard Cox</hi> (whom afterwards he preferred to the Deanry of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and made chief <hi>Almoner.)</hi> Theſe two being in Authority, employed themſelves to his advantage in their ſeveral kinds; Dr <hi>Cox,</hi> for knowledge of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Philoſophy and Gravity of Manners; Mr <hi>Cheek</hi> for Eloquence in the Greek and Latin Tongues. Beſides which two, he had ſome others to inſtruct him in the modern languages, and thrived ſo well amongſt them all, that in ſhort time he perfectly ſpake the French tongue, and was able to expreſſe himſelf ſignificantly enough in the Italian, Greek and Spaniſh. And as for the Latin, how early a Proficient he was therein (with reference to the times wherein he lived) is yet to be ſeen in ſome Latin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piſtles of his written to the King and others, before he was eight years old.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For a Companion at his book, or rather for aproxy to bear the puniſhment of ſuch errors as either through negligence or inadvertency were committed by him, he had one <hi>Barnaby Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patrick.</hi> He had a very eaſie ſubſtitution of it. And, if it ſometimes happened, as it ſeldom did, that the ſervant ſuffered puniſhment for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters errors; it is not eaſie to affirm, whether <hi>Fitzpatrick</hi> ſmarted more for the fault of the Prince, or the Prince conceived more grief for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:187791:7"/> the ſmart of <hi>Fitz-patrick.</hi> Certain it is, that the Prince entertaind ſuch a real eſtimation of him, that when he came unto the Crown, he acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him by letters with the ſufferings of the Duke of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> inſtructed and maintained him for his travels in <hi>France,</hi> endowed him with fair lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> his native Country; and finally made him Baron of upper <hi>Oſſory:</hi> which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Title he enjoyed till the time of his death, in the later end of Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> raign; at which time he dyed a zealous and Religious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant.</p>
            <p n="5">5. One thing I muſt not pretermit to ſhew the extraordinary piety of this hopeful Prince in the daies of his childhood; when, being about to take down ſomewhat, which ſeemed to be above his reach, one of his ſervants proferd him a boſſed plated Bible, to ſtand upon and heighten him: Which, when he perceived to be a Bible, with holy Indignation he refuſed to do; but took it, and kiſt it, and laid it in its place, ſharply reprehending him that made the offer. A ſtrong aſſurance of that dear eſteem and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in which he held that Sacred book in his riper years.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Having attained the Age of nine, there were great preparations made for his ſolemn Inveſtiture in the principality of <hi>Wales:</hi> But ſcarce were the proviſions ready, but the Kings ſickneſs brought
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:187791:7"/> a ſtop, and His death ſhortly after put an end to thoſe preparations; the expectation of a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality, being thereby changed to the poſſeſſion of a Crown.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It cannot be denyed, but that King <hi>Henry</hi> left the Church, in many reſpects, in a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then he found it; not only in order to the Reformation of Religion, which none but ſuch a maſculin Prince durſt have undertaken, but alſo in the policy and endowments of it. The Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries and Religious Houſes might poſſibly be lookt upon no otherwiſe, then as ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcences upon the body of the Church: but, Biſhopricks being more eſſential to the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame, he did not onely preſerve, as before he found them, but encreaſe their number. Six of the wealthier Monaſteries he turned into Epiſcopal Sees, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Abbies of <hi>Weſtminſter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eterborough, Bristol, Gloceſter</hi> and <hi>Cheſter,</hi> with that of <hi>Ouſney,</hi> for the See of the Biſhop of <hi>Oxon;</hi> aſſigning to every new Epiſcopal See its Dean and Chapter, and unto every ſuch Cathedral, a competent number of Quire-men and other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, all of them liberally endowed and provided for. And that the Church might be continually furniſhed with ſufficient Seminaries; he foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Grammar School in every one of his Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drals, either old or new, with Annual Penſions to the Maſter and ſome allowance to be made to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:187791:8"/> Children yearly; and ordained alſo, that in each of the two Univerſities there ſhould be publick Readers, in the faculties of Divinity, Law and Phyſick, and in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongues: all which he penſioned, and endowed with liberal Salaries, as the times then were. Beſides which publick benefactions, he confirmed Cardinal <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey's</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxon,</hi> by the name of Kings Colledge firſt, and of Chriſt-Church afterwards; and erected that moſt beautifull pile of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge:</hi> Thoſe being the two faireſt, and moſt magnificent Foundations in the Chriſtian World. And as for the polity of the Church, he ſettled it in ſuch a manner, that Archbiſhops and Biſhops might be choſen, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, and all the Subjects relieved in their Sutes and Grievances, without having ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as formerly had drained the Realm of ſo much Treaſure.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Earl of <hi>Hartford</hi> (after, Duke of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet)</hi> the young Kings Uncle, is choſen Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of his Perſon, and Protector of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, till he ſhould come to the Age of eighteen years. The Protector and other Grandees of the Court preſently entertain ſome thoughts of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. In which they found Arch-biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and ſome other Biſhops to be as forward as themſelves: but, on different ends: endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the Biſhops, in a pious zeal for recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:187791:8"/> ſuch things as were amiſs in God's publick Worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but by the Courtiers, on an hope to enrich themſelves by the ſpoil of the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Commiſſioners are ſent forth into all parts of the Kingdom, armed with Inſtructions to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into all Eccleſiaſtical Concernments, in the manner of a Viſitation; directed by the King, as Supreme Head on Earth of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Which Commiſſioners, being directed into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Circuits, were accompanied with certain learned and godly Preachers, appointed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the people, and to facilitate the work of the Commiſſioners in all Towns and Places, where they ſate. And, that the people might not cool or fall off again, in, and from that which had been taught them by the learned Preachers, they were to leave ſome Homilies to the ſame effect with the Pariſh-Prieſts: which the Arch-biſhop had compoſed; not only for the help of unpreaching Miniſters, but for the regulating and enſtructing even of learned Preachers. The Preachers were more particularly inſtructed to perſwade the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from praying to Saints, from Adoring of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, from praying in unknown Language, and ſome other like things whereunto long Cuſtom had brought a Religious Obſervation. All which was done to this intent; That the people in all places being prepared by little and little, might
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:187791:9"/> with more eaſe and leſſe oppoſition admit the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Alteration in the face of the Church, which was intended in due time to be introduced. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Injunctions ſent with the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were theſe following. <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>That the laws for aboliſhing the Popes uſurped Power be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: That the people be exhorted to works of Faith, Mercy and Charity: That Images be taken down: That the Bible in Engliſh, and <hi>Eraſmus</hi> Paraphraſe be placed in the Church: That Eccleſiaſtical perſons ptomoted give ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions to poor Scholars in the Univerſities: That no Eccleſiaſtical perſon haunt Ale-houſes. That none preach without licence: That no Curate admit to the Communion ſuch who are in malice with their Neighbours: That the Holy Day be wholly given to God, except in times of harveſt: That Tithes be not detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: That Prieſts be not abuſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. The famous Preacher at Court was Father <hi>Latimer:</hi> who drew ſuch multitudes of people after him to hear his Sermons; that being to preach before the King on the firſt Friday in Lent, it was thought neceſſary, that the Pulpit ſhould be placed in the Kings Privy-garden, where he might be heard of more then four times as many Auditors, as could have thronged into the Chappel. In which place was erected afterwards a fixed and ſtanding Pulpit for the like
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:187791:9"/> occaſions: eſpecially for Lent-Sermons on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies in the Afternoon: and hath ſo continued ever ſince, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l theſe later times.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In the ſecond of his raign, <hi>An.</hi> 1548. his Majeſtie declared by Proclamation <hi>Septemb.</hi> 23. <q>That for the ſetling of an Uniformity and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der throughout his Realm; and for putting an end to all Controverſies in Religion, He had cauſed certain Godly Biſhops and other notable learned men to be Congregated, or called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And thereupon doth infer: That, notwithſtanding many of the Preachers, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly licenſed, had behaved themſelves very diſcreetly and wiſely, to the Honour of God and the contentation of his Highneſſe: Yet till ſuch time, as the ſaid Order ſhould be generally ſet forth throughout the Realm. His Majeſty did thereby inhibit all manner of Perſons, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, to preach in open Audience, in the Pulpit or otherwiſe, by any ſought colour or fraud, to the diſobeying of his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And this he did to the intent; That the Whole Clergy in the mean ſpace might apply themſelves to prayer to Almighty God for the better atchieving of this ſame Godly intent and purpoſe; Not doubting but that all his loving Subjects in the mean time would occupy themſelves to Gods honour, with due prayer in the Church, and patient hearing of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:187791:10"/> the Godly Homilies: and ſo endeavour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they may be the more ready, with thankful Obedience to receive a moſt quiet, godly and uniform Order throughout all his Realms and Dominions.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Here it is to be obſerved, That thoſe who had the chief directing of this weighty bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were before hand reſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved, that none but Engliſh heads or hands ſhould be uſed therein: le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t otherwiſe it might be thought, and perhaps objected, That they rather followed the example of ſome other Churches, or were ſwayed by the Authority of thoſe forein Aſſiſtants, then by the Word of God, and the moſt uncorrupted practice of the Primitive Times. And though it was thought neceſſary, for the better ſeaſoning of the Univerſities in the Proteſtant Reformed Religion, that <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> two emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divines of the forein Churches, ſhould be invited to come over: yet we find neither of them here, till the end of <hi>November</hi> (1548) when the Liturgie had been approved of by the King and Council, if it had not alſo paſſed the Approbation of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The Book being finiſhed and ſubſcribed, it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s with all due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>everence humbly preſented to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing: by whom it was received to his great Comfort and Quietneſſe of mind, as the Statute telleth us: and being by him commended to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:187791:10"/> Lords and Commons then aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They did not only give his Highneſſe moſt hearty and lowly Thanks, for his Care therein; but, on peruſal thereof, declared it to be done by the aid of the Holy Ghoſt: and thereupon it was enacted, That all Miniſters in the Kings Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſhould ſay Common and open prayer in ſuch order and form, as is mentioned in the ſame Book, and no otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="14">14. The raign of this Young King was indeed remarkable for the progreſſe of the Reformation, but otherwiſe tumultuous in it ſelf, and defamed by Sacrilege, and ſo diſtracted into ſides and factions, that in the end the King himſelf became a prey to the ſtrongeſt party.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The Phyſicians that attended him on his death bed whiſpered: That neither their Advice nor Applications had been at all regarded in the courſe of his ſickneſſe: That the King had been ill dealt with, more than once or twice: and, That, when by the benefit both of his Youth and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means, there were ſome fair hopes of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, he was again more ſtrongly overlaid than ever. It is affirmed by a Writer of the Popiſh party, (who could have no great cauſe to pity ſuch a calamitous end) that the Apothecary who poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſond him, for the horrour of the offenſe, and the diſquietneſſe of his Conſcience, did, not long after, drown himſelf.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:187791:11"/> 16. In his dying prayer (as it was taken from his Mouth) we have thoſe pious words: <hi>Lord God, deliver me out of this miſerable and wretched life, and take me among thy Choſen. Howbeit not my will, but thine be done. Lord, Bleſſe my people, and ſave thine inheritance. Defend this Realm from Papistry, and maintain thy true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> 6. <hi>Jul. An, D.</hi> 1553. <hi>Aet.</hi> 16.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:12"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Nata 1537. cc Regina Declaritur Guildfordice Dudley 1553 Iul: 10. Conjugata Capite Plectitur 1553. Maij. 1553/4. Feb: 12.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for Rich<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Chiſwell at the Roſe and Crown in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls Church yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="biography">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:187791:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>II. The Lady <hi>JANE GREY.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of Dr</hi> Heylins <hi>Hiſtory of the Reformation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. SHe was eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Henry L. Grey,</hi> Duke of <hi>Suffolk.</hi> Her Mother was the <hi>Ladie Francis,</hi> daughter, and in fine one of the coheires of <hi>Charles Brandon,</hi> the late Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> by <hi>Marie</hi> his wife, Queen <hi>Dowager</hi> to <hi>Lewis</hi> 12. of <hi>France,</hi> and youngeſt Daughter of K. <hi>Henrie</hi> VII. She ſeemed to have been born with thoſe Attractions, which ſeat a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigntie</hi> in the face of moſt beautiful perſons: yet was her <hi>Mind</hi> endued with more excellent Charms, then the Attractions of her <hi>Face:</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and Mild of Diſpoſition, Courteous of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and of ſuch Affable Deportment, as might
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:187791:13"/> entitle her to the name of <hi>Queen of Hearts,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe was deſigned for Queen over any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe her Native and obliging <hi>Graces,</hi> were accompanied with ſome more profitable ones, of her own acquiring: which ſet an higher value on them, and much encreaſed the ſame, both in Worth and Luſtre. Having attained unto that Age, in which other young Ladies uſed to apply themſelves to the ſports and exerciſes of their Sex, She wholly gave her Mind to good <hi>Arts and Sciences;</hi> much furthered in that purſuit by the loving Care of Mr <hi>Elmer:</hi> under whoſe charge ſhe came to ſuch a large proficiency, that ſhe ſpake the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Tongues, with as ſweet a <hi>fluencie,</hi> as if they had been natural and native to her: exactly skilled in the liberal Sciences, and perfectly well ſtudied in both kinds of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Take here a ſtory out of Mr <hi>Aſcham</hi>'s Schoolm. p. 11. in his own words: <q>One exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Whether love or fear doth work more in a child, for vertue and learning, I will gladly report: which may be heard with ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and followed with more profit. Before <hi>I</hi> went into <hi>Germanie, I</hi> came to <hi>Brodegate</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> to take my leave of that noble <hi>Ladie Jane Grey,</hi> to whom <hi>I</hi> was exceeding much beholding. Her Parents the Duke and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:187791:13"/> Dutcheſſe, with all the Houſhold, Gentlemen and Gentlewomen, were hunting in the Park: <hi>I</hi> found her in her Chamber, reading <hi>Phoedon Platonis</hi> in Greek, and that with as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, as ſome Gentlemen would read a merry tale in <hi>Bocace.</hi> After ſalutation, and duty done, with ſome other talk, <hi>I</hi> asked her, why ſhe would leeſe ſuch paſtime in the Park: Smiling ſhe anſwered me; <hi>I</hi> wiſſe, all their <hi>ſport</hi> in the Park, is but a <hi>ſhadow</hi> to that pleaſure that <hi>I</hi> find in <hi>Plato:</hi> Alas, good folk, they never felt what true pleaſure meant. And how came You, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, quoth <hi>I,</hi> to this deep knowledge of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and what did chiefly allure You unto it, ſeeing not many women, but very few men have attained thereunto. <hi>I</hi> will tel you, ſaith ſhe, and tell you a troth, which perchance ye will marvel at. One of the greateſt benefits that ever God gave me, is, that he ſent me ſo ſharp and ſevere Parents, and ſo gentle a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter. For, when <hi>I</hi> am in preſence either of Father or Mother, whether <hi>I</hi> ſpeak, keep ſilence, ſit, ſtand, or go, eat, drink, be merry, or ſad, be ſowing, playing, dauncing, or doing any thing elſe, <hi>I</hi> muſt do it, as it were, in ſuch weight, meaſure and number, even ſo perfectly, as God made the world; or elſe <hi>I</hi> am ſo ſharply traunted, ſo cruelly threatned, yea preſently ſometimes, with pinches, nips and bobs, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:187791:14"/> waies, (which <hi>I</hi> will not name, for the honour <hi>I</hi> bear them,) ſo without meaſure miſordered, that <hi>I</hi> think my ſelf in hell, till time come, that I muſt go to Mr <hi>Elmer:</hi> who teacheth me ſo gently, ſo pleaſantly, with ſuch fair allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to learning, that I think all the time nothing, whiles I am with him. And when I am called from him, I fall on weeping, becauſe, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I do elſe, but <hi>learning,</hi> is full of grief, trouble, fear and whole miſliking unto me. And thus my <hi>book</hi> hath been ſo much my <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and bringeth dayly to me more pleaſure and more, that in reſpect of it, all other pleaſures, in very deed, be but trifles and troubles unto me. I remember this talk gladly, both becauſe it is ſo worthy of memory, and becauſe alſo it was the laſt talk that ever I had, and the laſt time that ever <hi>I</hi> ſaw that noble and worthy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Thus far Mr <hi>Aſcham.]</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. By this eminent proficiency in all parts of learning, and an Agreeableneſſe in Diſpoſition, ſhe became very dear to the Young K. <hi>Edward:</hi> to whom <hi>Fox</hi> not onely makes her equal, but doth acknowledge her alſo to be his Superiour in thoſe noble ſtudies. And for an Ornament ſuperadded to her other perfections, ſhe was moſt zealouſly affected to the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> then by law eſtabliſhed; Which ſhe embraced, not out of any outward compliance with the preſent cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:187791:14"/> of the Times, but becauſe her own mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t excellent Judgement had been fully ſatisfied in the Truth and Purity thereof. All which did ſo endear her to the King, that he took great delight in her Converſation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thus lived ſhe in theſe ſweet Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, till ſhe came unto the years of <hi>Marriage,</hi> when ſhe, that never found in her ſelf the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſpark of Ambition, was made the moſt unhappy Inſtrument of another Mans. The proud and aſpiring Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> treats with the Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> about a Marriage between the Lord <hi>Guilford Dudly</hi> his fourth Son, and the <hi>Lady Jane.</hi> The Marriage is concluded, and by <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi>'s policy; the <hi>Crown</hi> is transferred from K. <hi>Edward</hi> to his Coſin the Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> his two Siſters the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> and Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being paſſed by. Memorable is the Speech ſhe made to the two Dukes, when they owned her for Queen, to this effect: <q>That the Laws of the Kingdom, and natural Right, ſtanding for the Kings Siſters, ſhe would beware of burthening her weak Conſcience with a yoke, which did belo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g to them: That ſhe underſtood the Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of thoſe, who had permitted the violation of Right, to gain a Scepter: That it were to mock God, and deride Juſtice, to ſcruple at the ſtealing of a ſhilling, and not at the uſurpation of a Crown. Beſides (ſaid ſhe) I am not ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:187791:15"/> yong, nor ſo little read in the guiles of fortune, to ſuffer my ſelf to be taken by them. If ſhe enrich any, it is but to make them the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of her ſpoil: If ſhe raiſe others, it is but to pleaſure her ſelf with their Ruins. What ſhe adored but yeſterday, is to day her paſtime. And if I now permit her to adorn and Crown Me, I muſt to morrow ſuffer her to cruſh, and tear me in pieces, &amp;c. But the Ambition of the two</q> Dukes was too ſtrong and violent, to be kept down by any ſuch prudent Conſiderations. So that being wearied at laſt with their <hi>Importunities,</hi> and overcome by the intreaties of her husband, whom ſhe dearly loved, She ſubmitted unto that neceſſity which ſhe could not vanquiſh, yielding her <hi>head</hi> with more unwillingneſſe to the raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glories of a <hi>Crown,</hi> then afterward ſhe did to the ſtroke of the <hi>Ax.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Acclamations</hi> at the proclaiming of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> were heard by the <hi>Lady Jane</hi> (now no longer Queen) with ſuch Tranquillity of mind and compoſedneſſe of countenance, as if ſhe had not been <hi>concerned</hi> in the Alteration. She had before received the offer of a <hi>Crown,</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s even a Temper, as if it had been nothing, but a <hi>Garland of flowers:</hi> and now ſhe layes aſide the thought thereof with as much contentedneſs, as ſhe could have thrown away that Garland when the ſent was gone. The time of her Glory was ſo ſhort, but <hi>a</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:187791:15"/> 
               <hi>nine Daies wonder,</hi> that it ſeemed nothing but a Dream, out of which ſhe was not ſorry to be awakened. The Towr had been to her a <hi>priſon,</hi> rather than a <hi>Court,</hi> and interrupted the Delights of her former life by ſo many Terrours, that no Day paſſed without ſome new Alarm to diſturb her Quiet. She doth now know the worſt that fortune can do unto her: and having alwaies fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that there ſtood a <hi>Scaffold</hi> ſecretly behind the <hi>Throne,</hi> She was as readily prepared to act her part upon the one, as upon the other.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Her <hi>Death</hi> is reſolved upon: but firſt She muſt be practiced with to change her <hi>Religion.</hi> To which end <hi>Fecknam</hi> is employed: a Man, whoſe great parts ptomiſed him an eaſie victory over a poor Lady of a broken and dejected Spirit. But it proved the contrary. For, ſo well had She ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed the <hi>Concernments</hi> of her own Religion, and managed the <hi>Conference</hi> with him, with ſuch a readineſſe of <hi>wit,</hi> ſuch Conſtancie of <hi>Reſolution,</hi> and a <hi>Judgement</hi> ſo well grounded in all helps of Learning; that ſhe was able to make <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the ſtrongeſt Arguments; as well to her great Honour, as his Admiration. So that, not able to prevail with her in the change of Religion, he made offer of his ſervice to prepare her for death. Which, though ſhe thankfully accepted of, as finding it to proceed from a good affection; yet ſoon he found, that ſhe was alſo aforehand with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:187791:16"/> him in thoſe preparations, which are fit and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for a Dying-Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Friday, 9. <hi>Febr.</hi> was firſt deſigned for the day of the <hi>Execution:</hi> but the Deſire of gaining her to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> procured her the ſhort reſpite of three dayes more. On Sunday night, being the Eve unto the day of her <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> ſhe wrote a Letter in the <hi>Greek</hi> tongue, at the end of a Teſtament, which ſhe bequeathed as a <hi>Legacy</hi> to her Siſter the Lady <hi>Katharine,</hi> which being ſuch a lively Picture of the excellent Lady, ſome lines thereof are worthy to be preſented here: <q>I have ſent you a <hi>Book</hi> (dear Siſter) which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be not outwardly trimmed with <hi>Gold,</hi> yet inwardly it is more worth then <hi>pretious ſtones.</hi> If you with a good <hi>mind</hi> read it, and with an earneſt deſire to follow it, it ſhall bring you to an immortal and everlaſting life: it ſhall teach you to <hi>live,</hi> and learn you to <hi>dy:</hi> it ſhall win you more, then you ſhould have gained by your wofull Fathers Lands. You ſhall be an Inheritor of ſuch <hi>Riches,</hi> as neither the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous</hi> ſhall withdraw from you, neither <hi>Thief</hi> ſhall ſteal, neither yet the <hi>Moths</hi> corrupt. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire with <hi>David</hi> (good Siſter) to underſtand the Law of the Lord God. Live ſtill to dy, that you by <hi>death</hi> may purchaſe eternal <hi>life.</hi> Defie the <hi>world:</hi> Deny the <hi>Devil:</hi> Deſpiſe the <hi>Fleſh;</hi> and delight your ſelf only in the Lord. Be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:187791:16"/> for your ſins, and yet <hi>deſpair</hi> not. Be ſtrong in Faith, and yet <hi>preſume</hi> not. And <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> with Saint <hi>Paul, to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt,</hi> with whom, even in death, there is life. And as touching my death, rejoyce as I do (Good Siſter) that I ſhall be deliver'd of this <hi>Corruption,</hi> and put on <hi>Incorruption,</hi> For I am aſſured, that I ſhall, for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a mortal life, win an immortal one. The which I pray God to grant you, and ſend you of his Grace, to live in his fear, and to dy in the true Chriſtian <hi>Faith:</hi> from the which, in Gods name, I exhort you, that you never ſwerve, neither for hope of life, nor for fear of death.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. The fatal Morning being come, the Lord <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> earneſtly deſired the <hi>officers,</hi> that he might take his <hi>Farewell</hi> of her. Which, though they willingly permitted, yet, upon notice of it, ſhe adviſed the contrary, aſſuring him, <q>That ſuch a <hi>Meeting</hi> would rather add to his Afflictions, and her preſence rather weaken then ſtrengthen him: That he ought to take courage from his <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and derive conſtancy from his own <hi>heart:</hi> That he ſhould do well to remit this <hi>Interview</hi> to the other World; that there indeed Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips were happy, and unions indiſſoluble, and that theirs would be eternal, if their <hi>ſouls</hi> carried nothing with them of Terreſtrial, which might
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:187791:17"/> hinder them from rejoycing.</q> All ſhe could do, was to give him a <hi>Farewell</hi> out of a window, as he paſſed toward the place of his diſſolution: which he ſuffer'd on the Scaffold on <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> with much Chriſtian meekneſſe.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Lady was led to a Scaffold within the <hi>Tower,</hi> by Sir <hi>Henry Gage</hi> the Conſtable; who deſired her to beſtow ſome ſmall <hi>gift</hi> upon him, as a <hi>Memorial</hi> of her. To gratify which deſire, ſhe gave him her <hi>Table-book:</hi> in which ſhe had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten three ſentences, in <hi>Greek, Latine and Engliſh;</hi> as ſhe ſaw her Husbands Body brought unto the Chappel; which ſhe beſought him to accept as her laſt Bequeſt. The <hi>Greek</hi> to this effect: <q>That, if his executed <hi>body</hi> ſhould give teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt her before Men; his moſt bleſſed <hi>ſoul</hi> ſhould give an eternal proof of her Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in the preſence of God. The <hi>Latine</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: That <hi>Humane Juſtice</hi> was againſt his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but the <hi>Divine Mercy</hi> would be for his Soul. The Concluſion in Engliſh: That, if her <hi>fault</hi> deſerved puniſhment, her <hi>Youth</hi> at leaſt, and her Imprudence were worthy of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; and, that <hi>God and Poſterity</hi> would ſhew her Favour.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Conducted by <hi>Fecknam</hi> to the Scaffold, ſhe gave not much heed to his Diſcourſes, but kept her eyes upon a <hi>Prayer-book</hi> of her own. And, being mounted on the <hi>Throne,</hi> from which ſhe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:187791:17"/> was to receive a more excellent <hi>Crown,</hi> then any which this vile Earth could give her, ſhe addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelf in ſome few words to the ſtanders by, letting them know; <q>That her offence was not for having layd her hand upon the Crown, but for <hi>not rejecting</hi> it with ſufficient Conſtancy: That ſhe had leſſe erred through <hi>Ambition,</hi> then out of <hi>Reverence</hi> to her parents; yet ſuch Reverence deſerved puniſhment: That ſhe would willingly admit of death, ſo to give <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to the injured State: And that ſhe had juſtly deſerved this puniſhment, for being made the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> (though an <hi>unwilling</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument) of Anothers ambition.</q> Then, having deſired the people to recommend her in their prayers to the mercies of God, being ready for the <hi>block,</hi> with the ſame clear and untroubled Countenance, wherewith ſhe had acted all the reſt of her <hi>Tragedy,</hi> ſhe ſaid aloud the Pſalm of <hi>Miſerere mei Deus,</hi> in the Engliſh Tongue, and ſo ſubmitted her pure neck to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xecutioner. <hi>An.</hi> 1553.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Miraris</hi> Janam Graio <hi>Sermone loquntam?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quo primum nata eſt tempore,</hi> Graia <hi>fuit.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Camd. in Reliq.</bibl>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="biography">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:187791:18"/>
            <head>III. Sir <hi>JOHN CHEEK.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his Life prefixed to</hi> The hurt of Sedition, <hi>written by Dr.</hi> Langbane.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THIS learned and worthy man fell im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, from the womb of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, into the lap of the Muſes; being both born and bred within the liberties of that famous nurſery of good Letters, <hi>Cambridge.</hi> He ſeems to have been of no vulgar extraction, for two of his Siſters were fairly matched, one to Dr. <hi>Blith,</hi> the Kings profeſſor of Phyſick; and <hi>Mary,</hi> another of them, to <hi>William Cecil,</hi> afterwards Lord <hi>Burghley,</hi> a moſt able Miniſter of State.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Ingenium magni moderatus Principis exul CHECVS, at inconstans in Pietate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p n="3">3. In the diſcharge of this later he went over all <hi>Sophocles</hi> twice, all <hi>Homer,</hi> all <hi>Euripides,</hi> and part of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> to his Auditors benefit and his own credit: which was all the Salary he then had: till King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII of his royal bounty endowed that and the other Chairs with the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Allowance of XL pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> and, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſole Commendatories of his former deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, conferred that honour on him, to be the firſt <hi>Regius profeſſor</hi> of the Greek tongue in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> as Sir <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> was of Law.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe two eſpecially by their advice and example brought the ſtudy of Tongues and other politer learning firſt into requeſt in that Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. Upon hopes of facilitating the Greek Tongue, they attempted to reduce it to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, but obſolete manner of pronuntiation: an innovation quickly obſerved by B. <hi>Gardiner,</hi> the Chancellor, and repreſſed by a ſtrict Injunction, <hi>May</hi> 21. 1542. And though at laſt, after ſeveral Writings, Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi> was content to ſubmit to that one unanſwerable Argument of the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors <hi>Authority;</hi> yet his Rules and Practice had taken ſuch deep root in his Auditors, that by them it was propagated through this whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:187791:20"/> and that we Engliſh-men ſpeak Greek, and are able to underſtand one another, we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be a ſpecial effect of Mr. <hi>Cheek's</hi> rare ingeny.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That famous King, <hi>Henry</hi> VIII, thought it ſit to call this great light of Learning out of the ſhadow: and ſo he did <hi>July</hi> 10. 1544. and to his Cuſtody he then committed the moſt precious Jewel of the Kingdom, the young Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> being at that time not full ſeven years of age. What progreſſe he made under this Director of his ſtudies, appears by thoſe noble Reliques of his induſtry und ſufficiency, both in Greek and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, which are ſtill preſerved in his Majeſties Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary at S. <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. It may be truly ſaid, that under God Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi> was a ſpecial Inſtrument of the propagation of the Goſpel, and that Religion which we now profeſſe in this Kingdom. For he not only ſowed the ſeeds of that Doctrin in the heart of Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> which afterwards grew up into a general Reformation when he came to be King; but by his means the ſame ſaving truth was gently inſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by thoſe who by his procurement were admitted to be guides of her younger ſtudies. Such were, firſt <hi>William Grindall,</hi> and after him <hi>Roger Aſcham,</hi> who had fomerrly bin his Scholar in the Coll. and ſucceſſor in the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors place in the Univerſity: a man dear unto him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:187791:20"/> for ſimilitude of ſtudies, but more for his zeal to the true Religion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>An.</hi> 1547. When the young King was wel ſettled in his Throne, he admitted Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi> to be one of his privy Chamber. This accrue of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to her ſon made his learned Mother the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity a ſuiter to him for protection in thoſe ſtormy times: who in her Letters to him gives him ſuch an Elogie, as muſt not be omitted here. This it is: <hi>Ex univerſo illo numero clariſſimorum virorum (Clariſſimè Chece) qui ex hac Academia in Remp. unquam prodierunt, Tu unus es, quem ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Academia, prae univerſis aliis, &amp; praeſentem complexa eſt, &amp; abſentem admirata eſt: qnam Tu viciſſim pluſquam univerſi alii &amp; praeſens ornave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, &amp; abſens juvas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1551. When his Majeſty was pleaſed to make a doal of Honours among his deſerving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi> was not forgotten: He, with his Brother in Law Secretary <hi>Cecil,</hi> were then Knighted, This was but a foundation upon which the gratefull Prince had a purpoſe to erect high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er preferments, had not the hand of Providence ſo ſoon ſnatcht him away into another Kingdom, to inveſt his temples with a more glorious Crown. This was done <hi>July</hi> 6. 1553. not long after he had called Sir <hi>John Cheek</hi> to ſit at the helm of State, the Council Boord. In this common loſſe of ſo good a King, He, good man, had more then a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:187791:21"/> ſhare. Being clapt up in priſon <hi>July</hi> 27. he was ſtript of the greateſt part of his honours, and all his fortunes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut his Perſon was ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. and not long after we meet with him in <hi>Germany,</hi> either a forced or a voluntary exile.</p>
            <p n="9">9. From thence he paſſed into <hi>Italy,</hi> and by the way left thoſe adverſary Epiſtles of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and himſelf with his Friend <hi>Coelius,</hi> who put them in print without the Authours pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. At his return to <hi>Germany,</hi> he was kindly entertained at <hi>Strasburg,</hi> where he took up his old trade, and ſet up ſhop again, being choſen Profeſſor of the Greek tongue in that place. This was a treaſure which maintained him in his exile: this he had not confiſcate to the Queen: this eſcaped the diligence of the Searchers, when he conveyed it out of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Here he lived about two years in good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, till I know not what unlucky ſtars put him upon a journey into the Low Countries. Some have ſaid it was to marry a wife: but what need of that, when he was already matched to a young Lady; who lived to ſee many happier days after his deceaſe, and dyed well nigh threeſcore years after him, <hi>An.</hi> 1616. <hi>Sleidan</hi> tells us he went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to low <hi>Germany, ut uxorem educeret,</hi> to fetch his wife thence, who belike was lately come over out of <hi>England,</hi> and meant to ſettle with him at <hi>Strasburg.</hi> But in his return from <hi>Bruxelles</hi> to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:187791:21"/> 
               <hi>Antwerp, May</hi> 15. 1556, both Sir <hi>John Cheek</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Carew</hi> were way-laid by the Provoſt Marſhall for K. <hi>Philip,</hi> beaten from their horſes, tyed hand and foot to the bottom of a Cart, and ſo conveyed hood-winkt to the next Haven; where they were ſhipt under h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tches, and their firſt landing place was the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> where they were committed to cloſe priſon. Sir <hi>Peter Carew</hi> out-lived his Troubles, and under-went many honourable ſervices under Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and dyed <hi>An.</hi> 1575.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Sir <hi>John Cheek's</hi> lot was ſomewhat harder: he was put to this miſerable choiſe, either to forgo his life, or what is far more precious, his liberty of Conſcience. No mean: neither his great Learning, nor his known integrity, nor the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of his friends, and among them Abbot <hi>Fekenham</hi> (a man which could do ſomewhat with Queen <hi>Mary)</hi> could compound for his pardon at any lower rate, then the recantation of his Religion. Upon this he was ſoon reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his liberty, but never to his content. The ſenſe and ſorrow for himſelf, and the dayly ſight of that cruel butchery which was exerciſed upon others for the conſtant profeſſion of the truth, made ſuch deep impreſſions in his broken ſoul, as brought him to a ſpeedy, but comfortable end of a miſerable life.</p>
            <p n="12">12. He dyed at <hi>London</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:187791:22"/> 
               <hi>Oſbern</hi> Eſq; <hi>Sept.</hi> 1557. He left one Son, which bare his name, a comely young man and a ſtout, ſlain in his Princes ſervice in <hi>Ireland</hi> 1580. but the iſſue of his brain was more numerous; <hi>De pronuntiatione Graecae linguae, Panegyricus Edvardi VI. De obitu Buceri, De Euchariſtiae Sacramento, Maximi Monachi Aſceticus,</hi> &amp;c. His Body lyes buryed at Saint <hi>Albans, Wood-ſtreet,</hi> with this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaph:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Doctrinae Checus linguaeque utriuſque Magiſter,</l>
               <l>Aurea naturae fabrica morte jacet.</l>
               <l>Non erat è multis unus, ſed praeſtitit unus</l>
               <l>Omnibus, &amp; patriae flos erat ille ſuae.</l>
               <l>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma Britanna fuit: tam magnum nulla tulerunt</l>
               <l>Tempora the ſaurum: tempora nulla ferent.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:23"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>IOHANNES WHITGIFTVS ARCHEP.</hi> Whitgiftus rup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is vinclis Romana relinguens Sacra pius, ſeſe meliores vertit ad vſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="biography">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:187791:23"/>
            <head>IV. Dr. <hi>JOHN WHITGIFT</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his life written by Sir</hi> George Paul, <hi>Controller of his Graces houſhold.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. HE came of the antient family of <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift of Whitgift</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> the eldeſt ſon of a Merchant <hi>Henry Whitgift</hi> of great <hi>Grimſly</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> and was there born <hi>An.</hi> 1530. He was taught (among other young Gentlemen) by his Unkle <hi>Robert Whitgift</hi> Abbot of <hi>Wellow.</hi> In which time (as he was pleaſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to remember) he heard the Abbot ſay: <hi>That they and their Religion could not long continue; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I have read the whole Scripture over and over, and could never find therein that our Religion was founded by God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His Uncle finding an extraordinary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlyneſſe in him, ſent him afterwards, to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> where he became a Scholar in <hi>S. Anthonies</hi> Schoole, and boarded at his Aunts Houſe in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:187791:24"/> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. From thence he repaired to <hi>Grimſly</hi> to his Parents, being thruſt out of dores by his Aunt, becauſe he would not goe with her to <hi>Maſs,</hi> imputing all her domeſtick misfortunes to her harbouring ſuch an <hi>Heretick</hi> in her Houſe: and for a <hi>Farewell</hi> told him; <hi>That ſhe thought at the firſt, ſhe had received a Saint into her Houſe, but now ſhe perceived he was a Divel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. His Parents finding his proficiency, by the direction of his Uncle, ſent him to <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Dr. <hi>Ridley</hi> made him Scholar of <hi>Pembroke Hall:</hi> thence, Dr. <hi>Pearn</hi> choſe him Fellow of <hi>Peter houſe:</hi> Being there fallen grievouſly ſick, the Doctor (who lov'd him for his good parts) pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him with a good woman near the Colledge, viſiting him oft, and charging her to ſpare no coſt for his recovery: <hi>If he lives</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>he will be able to pay you himſelf: if he dye, I will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. After his recovery, Dr. <hi>Pearn,</hi> finding he purpoſed to travel Beyond Sea to avoid the <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> ſent by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> conferred with him, and ſeeing him reſolute in his Religion, upon many good and ſound reaſons (as the Doctor of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten acknowledged) willed him <hi>to be ſilent, and quiet,</hi> and he would ſo order the matter, that he might keep his Religion and not leave the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity: which the good old man juſtly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:187791:24"/> 5. After he was entred into the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> (which was upon the year 1560) being to preach his firſt publick Sermon in S. <hi>Maries,</hi> he choſe for his Text that excellent ſaying of S. <hi>Paul, I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein his ſingular method, choice of matter, and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious handling thereof were ſuch, that his whole Auditory, eſpecially the Chief of the Univerſity, grew into great Admiration of thoſe great parts in ſo young years.</p>
            <p n="6">6. From being Fellow of <hi>Peter</hi> Houſe, he ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded Doctor <hi>Hutton</hi> in the Maſterſhip of <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke</hi> Hall, and being Chaplain to Doctor <hi>Cox</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> he had a <hi>Prebend</hi> there. He was alſo choſen the Lady <hi>Margarets Profeſſor</hi> of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and afterwards the Queens. The Queen, having heard him preach, ſaid he had a <hi>White gift</hi> indeed, made him Maſter of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge, and cauſed him immediately to be ſworn her Chaplain, <hi>An.</hi> 1567.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He govern'd the Colledge for five years ſpace with great quietneſſe, untill Mr. <hi>Tho. Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> (a Fellow of that Colledge) his laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from beyond the Seas. Whoſe firſt diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment grew from the Queens neglect of him at a Diſputation before her Majeſty in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Maſter being from home, Mr. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> with ſome of his adherents made three
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:187791:25"/> Sermons upon one Sunday, and ſo vehemently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed againſt the Surplice and other Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that they of the Colledge at Evening Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, laid aſide their Surplices, three only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Doctor <hi>Whitgift,</hi> after that Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> had broached his dangerous Doctrin, uſed to confute it in the ſame Church, the next Sunday following, and ſettled the judgment of many; and fore-ſeeing theſe ſparks of ſedition, if not timely quenched, would grow to a great flame, often ſent to Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and in friendly manner adviſed him to ſurceaſe from thoſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: but finding him wilfull and obſtinate, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceited of himſelf and a deſpiſer of others that were not of his mind, and a refuſer of any fair tryal of his cauſe by Conference or writing; cauſed him to be expelled the Houſe, and deprived likewiſe of the <hi>Margarit</hi> Lecture: <hi>An.</hi> 1570.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Not long after, the <hi>Diſciplinarians</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a ſeditious Treatiſe entituled, <hi>An Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the Parliament:</hi> the ſummary of their opinions and ſlanders. And in regard of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe it found among the greener heads, given to novelty, Doctor <hi>Whitgift</hi> anſwers it. <hi>Cartwright</hi> replyes, and Doctor <hi>Whitgift</hi> defends his Anſwer. A ſecond Reply being publiſht by <hi>Cartwright,</hi> the Doctor addreſſes himſelf to anſwer that too, but is diſſuaded by his judicious friends, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:187791:25"/> eſpecially by Doctor <hi>Whitaker</hi> in a Letter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are theſe among other words concerning the Authour: <hi>Veris ludit, ſententiis dormitat, &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne indignus est, qui à quopiam docto refutetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. In his ten years Government of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge, Doctor <hi>Whitgift</hi> bred many excellent Scholars (ſix whereof were in his time <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and ſome great <hi>States-men:</hi> he procured an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of the <hi>Statutes</hi> of the Vniverſity; and as the cauſes he dealt in were alwaies juſt, ſo his ſucceſs was ever proſperous, through his wiſdom and ſtoutneſſe. And yet that <hi>ſtoutneſſe</hi> was ſo well tempered and mingled with his other vertue of <hi>mildneſſe</hi> and patience, that Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> made this true obſervation of him; <hi>He alwaies govern'd with that moderation, which uſeth by patience to ſuppreſſe boldneſſe, and to make them conquer that ſuffer:</hi> which well ſuted with his Motto, <hi>Vincit qui patitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>An.</hi> 1577. He was choſen to be Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> conſecrated 21. <hi>Apr.</hi> and having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken leave of the Vniverſity and Colledge by preaching of peace publickly and privately, he was in <hi>June</hi> following attended on his way to <hi>Worceſter</hi> by a great Troup of the chiefeſt perſons, full of ſorrow for their loſſe of ſo excellent a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. The <hi>Queen,</hi> to ſhew her Bounty and Love, forgave him his <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> and gave him the diſpoſing of all the <hi>Prebends</hi> of that Church du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Continuance there.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:187791:26"/> 13. He found the <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> at his firſt coming much impaired by his Predeceſſors, in long Leaſes and Grants: but that which moſt troubled him was the letting of the <hi>Rent Corne</hi> of his two beſt Mannors, <hi>Hollow</hi> and <hi>Grimley,</hi> the chief uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Biſhops hoſpitality. To redeem the ſaid Corn from a powerfull Tenant, the Biſhop was contented, by way of Compoſition to give three hundred pound out of his own purſe to have the leaſe ſurrendred.</p>
            <p n="14">14. There was ſuch mutual love between the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that they delighted to converſe much together. And if the Biſhop un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of any jar or diſcord, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould ſend for both parties (under pretence of ſome ſervice to be done) and make them friends. If they were froward againſt perſwaſion, he would interpoſe his Authority, as <hi>Vice Preſident of Wales</hi> (which place her Majeſty beſtowed on him ſhortly after he was made Biſhop) and threaten the obſtinate with impriſonment.</p>
            <p n="15">15. He had a ſpecial care of his own <hi>family</hi> (as behoved him) and of his <hi>Attendants</hi> neer unto him; and to avoid all colour of corruption would never receive informations or petitions in his private Chamber but abroad, by the Petitioners themſelves; in ſo much that a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of his Bed-chamber making requeſt he might have the delivery of <hi>Suitors Petitions,</hi> and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:187791:26"/> indorſe their Anſwers, he grew into ſuch diſlike, that he preſently diſcharged him.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Her Majeſty out of her experience of his wiſe and prudent Government, was pleaſed (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on complaint of the many diſcords and diſorders in the two Cathedral Churches of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Hereford)</hi> to direct two Commiſſions unto him for the <hi>viſiting</hi> of the ſaid Churches. He reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them both, and ordained them <hi>Statutes</hi> for their better Government.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Arch-biſhop <hi>Grindal,</hi> laboured him in moſt earneſt manner to accept of the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, being himſelf contented to ſhake off his cares, and receive from her Majeſty ſome yearly Penſion: which Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> utterly refuſed, and in preſence of the Queen her ſelf beſought pardon in not accepting thereof, upon any condition whatſoever, in the life time of the other. Whereupon the Queen was graciouſly pleaſed to ſay: <hi>As ſhe had made him an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, ſo he ſhould dye an Arch-biſhop:</hi> As he did ſhortly after.</p>
            <p n="18">18. He was advanced to the Arch-biſhoprick of <hi>Canterbury, Sept.</hi> 24. 1583. At his firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance he procured an Order for the abatement of his <hi>firſt fruits:</hi> he recover'd from the Queen a thouſand Acres of Land, and by abating the fines of his <hi>Impropriations</hi> encreaſed the Penſions of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:187791:27"/> 19. Her Majeſty commanded him to be vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and carefull for the reducing of <hi>Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> much ſtrengthened by his Predeceſſors connivency. Wherein he had much adoe, many conflicts, and was oppoſed by ſome great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages. Concerning whom he thus writeth: <q>I truſt thoſe that love me indeed, will not ſo light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt off their old friends for any of theſe new fangled and factious <hi>Sectaries,</hi> whoſe fruits are to make diviſion.—If my honourable friends ſhould forſake me, when I think to deſerve beſt and in a manner conſume my ſelf to ſatisfie that which God, her Majeſty and the Church requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of me, I ſhould be evil rewarded. <hi>Sed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liora ſpero.—</hi>The ſlanderous tongues of this uncharitable Sect, reported that I am become a <hi>Papiſt:</hi> but it proceedeth from their leudneſs, not any deſert of mine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But how is it poſſible that I ſhould perform the charge, which I have undertaken, after ſo long liberty, and lack of Diſcipline, if a few perſons, ſo meanly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified (as moſt of theſe factious <hi>Sectaries</hi> are) ſhould be countenanced againſt the whole ſtate of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of greateſt account both for learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, years, ſtaidneſſe, wiſdome, religion and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty; and open breakers and impugners of the Law, young in years, proud in conceit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious in diſpoſition, ſhould be maintained againſt their Governours ſeeking to reduce
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:187791:27"/> them to order and obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The day wil come, when all mens hearts ſhall be opened. In the mean time I will depend upon him, who never fiaileth thoſe, that put their truſt in him.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>An.</hi> 1587. <hi>Tho. Bromley</hi> (the then Lord Chancellor) dyed. Whereupon it pleaſed her Majeſty to diſcover her gracious inclination, to have made the <hi>Arch-biſhop Lord Chancellour of England.</hi> But he excuſing himſelf in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, that he was grown into years, and had the burthen of all Eccleſiaſtical buſineſſes laid upon his back (which was as much as one man could well undergoe, conſidering the troubles with ſo many <hi>Sectaries</hi> that were then-ſprung up) deſired to be ſpared; and beſought her Highneſſe to make choice of Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Hatton,</hi> who ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after was made <hi>Lord Chancellour</hi> in the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops houſe</hi> at <hi>Croydon;</hi> thereby the rather to grace the <hi>Arch-biſhop.</hi> His advancement did much ſtrengthen the Arch-biſhop and his friends, and withall, the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> and his deſignments came ſoon after to an end.</p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>An.</hi> 1588. Upon the death of the Farl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> the Chancellorſhip of <hi>Oxford</hi> being void, divers of the Heads and others of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity made known unto the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> their deſire to chufe him their <hi>Chancellour,</hi> although he was a <hi>Cambridge</hi> man. To whom he returned
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:187791:28"/> this Anſwer; <hi>That he was already their friend, whereof they might reſt aſſured, and therefore advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to make choice of ſome other in near place about the Queen, that might aſſiſt him on their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half; and both at the Council-board, and other places of Justice, right them many waies, both for the benefit of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and of their Colledges.</hi> And therewithall recommended unto them Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Hatton,</hi> being ſometime of that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity. Whom accordingly they did chuſe for their <hi>Chancellour,</hi> and whom the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> ever found a great <hi>Aſſiſtant</hi> in bridling and reforming the imtemperate humour of thoſe <hi>Noveliſts,</hi> who by the Countenance of ſome great perſonages were now grown to a ſtrong head.</p>
            <p n="22">22. It was in their <hi>Aſſemblies Claſſical</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical</hi> concluded, that the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> ſhould, within a time limited, be put in practice, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected all <hi>in one day</hi> by the Miniſters together with the people: whom thoſe <hi>Diſciplinarians</hi> bragged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be already enflamed with zeal to lend ſo many thouſand hands, for the advancement of their Cauſe. In their publick Sermons and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horcations (as in their private <hi>Conventicles)</hi> they did alienate the hearts of their Auditors from all obedience of the Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtrates. As namely Mr. <hi>Cartwright:</hi> who alſo in his prayer before his <hi>Sermons,</hi> uſed thus to ſay: <hi>Becauſe they</hi> (meaning the Biſhops) <hi>which ought to be</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:187791:28"/> 
               <hi>pillars in the Church, do band themſelves againſt Chriſt and his truth; therefore, O Lord, give us grace and power, all as one man, to ſet our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</hi> Which words, by way of <hi>Emphaſts,</hi> he would often repeat. And doth not <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dall</hi> threaren, that the Presbytery ſhall prevail, and come in by that way and means, as ſhall <hi>make all their hearts to ake,</hi> that ſhall withſtand or hinder the ſame.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Great was the <hi>temper and moderation</hi> of the good <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> in handling theſe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. In his time <hi>Brown</hi> was changed from his fanſies, and afterwards obtained a Benefice called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church</hi> in <hi>North-Hamptonſhire,</hi> where he became a painfull Preacher. He did not, though he might have blemiſhed with her Majeſty the reputations of ſome in great place for favouring the <hi>Libellers</hi> and <hi>Libels,</hi> which had ſtowage and vent in their Chambers. He procured at her Majeſties hands both pardon and diſmiſſion for Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> and the reſt out of their troubles. For which Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> held himſelf much obliged, and in his letters acknowledgeth <hi>his bond of moſt humble duty ſo much the ſtraiter, becauſe his Graces fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour proceeded from a frank diſpoſition, without any deſert of his own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. The Arch-biſhop hath been heard to ſay, <hi>That if Mr.</hi> Cartwright <hi>had not ſo far engaged himſelf, as he did, in the beginning, he thought veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:187791:29"/> 
               <hi>he would in his later time have been drawn to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.</hi> For, when he was freed from his troubles he often repaired to the <hi>Arch-biſhop,</hi> who uſed him kindly, and was contented to <hi>tolerate</hi> his preaching in <hi>Warwick</hi> divers years, upon his <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> that he would not impugn the laws, orders and government in this <hi>Church of England,</hi> but perſwade and procure, ſo much as he could, both publickly and privately, the eſtimation and peace of the ſame. Which albeit he accordingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, yet when her Majeſty underſtood by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> did preach again (though temperately, according to his promiſe made to the <hi>Arch-biſhop:)</hi> She would by no means endure his preaching any longer without <hi>ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption;</hi> and grew not a little offended with the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> for ſuch <hi>conniving</hi> at him. Not long after Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> dyed rich, as it was ſaid, by the benevolence and bounty of his followers.</p>
            <p n="25">25. An. 1592. After the death of Sir <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tton,</hi> Sir <hi>John Puckering</hi> was made <hi>Lord Keeper,</hi> who ſhewed himſelf a friend to the <hi>Church,</hi> to the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> and his proceedings, and acknowledged him a furtherer of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement. Sir <hi>Thomas Egerton</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Rolles</hi> ſucceeded him, 6. <hi>May.</hi> 1596. a lover of learning, and a moſt conſtant favourer of the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Church-government</hi> eſtabliſhed: as alſo a faithfull loving friend to the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> in all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:187791:29"/> his affairs: In ſo much as after his advancement to that honour, and that the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and the Arch-biſhop concurred together, being alſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrengthned by the friendſhip and love of Sir <hi>Robert Cecil</hi> Principal Secretary, he began to be fully revived again. And her <hi>Majeſty</hi> finding in him a zealous care, and faithfull performance of his duty, laid the burthen of the Church upon his ſhoulders, telling him: <hi>That, if any thing went amiſs, be it upon his ſoul and conſcience to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it: for ſhe had rid her hands, and looked that he ſhould yeeld an account, on her behalf, to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26. And now, though the Arch-biſhop was in this ſingular favour and grace with his Majeſty, ſo that he did all in all for the managing of <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-affairs,</hi> and diſpoſing of <hi>Biſhopricks,</hi> and other Eccleſiaſtical promotions; yet was he never puffed up with pride, nor did any thing violently againſt any man. For he ever obſerved this rule, <hi>That he would not wound, where he could not ſalve.</hi> So that it was truly noted by the Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> a great Counſellour, in the Star-chamber when <hi>Pickering</hi> was there cenſured for libelling againſt him after his death: <hi>That there was nothing more to be feared in his Government (eſpecially toward his later time) then his mildneſſe and clemency.</hi> And ſome younger ſpirits were of opinion that he was much to blame in that kind, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:187791:30"/> would be bold to tell him: <hi>That he knew not his own ſtrength with her Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. As you may perceive his <hi>clemency</hi> towards the irregular ſort, ſo, towards the conformable, he was carried with an exceeding tender reſpect and <hi>kindneſſe.</hi> He loved a learned <hi>Miniſter,</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and honeſt, with all his heart, framing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto that rule of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> which directeth a good Magiſtrate, <hi>to be as carefull in encouraging good men according to their merits, as in puniſhing the bad according to the quality of their offenſes.</hi> If he found a <hi>Scholar</hi> of extraordinary gifts or hopes, that out of <hi>wants</hi> grew diſcontented, and enclined to <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>Puritaniſm</hi> (as moſt of their diſcontentments and way-wardneſſe proceedeth thence) him would he gain both with ſupplies of <hi>mony</hi> out of his purſe, and <hi>preferments</hi> of his own gift, or otherwiſe as opportunity ſerved.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Neither was his <hi>Bounty</hi> wanting to men of learning and quality of <hi>forrein</hi> Countries. Sundry times ſent he mony to Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> out of his own purſe, beſides the general <hi>Collections</hi> for <hi>Geneva.</hi> Upon which occaſion many letters paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. In his letter <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. 1591. <hi>Beza</hi> confeſſeth: <hi>That he never intended to touch, or impugne the Eccleſiastical policy of this Church of</hi> England, <hi>nor to exact of us to frame our ſelves or our Church to the pattern of their Presbyterial Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That as Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>was the true</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:187791:30"/> 
               <hi>nurſing Mother of the Church of Chriſt, ſo</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and our Engliſh Church was both the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the Godly, and the preſerver of all other Reformed Churches.</hi> So far was he alſo from eſteeming the Arch-biſhop an <hi>Antichriſtian Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> as he never omitted to term him, <hi>A moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father in Chriſt, and his moſt honoured good Lord.</hi> I wiſh that our <hi>Diſciplinarians,</hi> who ſeem to direct themſelves by the <hi>rule of Geneva,</hi> would learn thus to <hi>Diſcipline</hi> their tongues with him, and imitate his <hi>Modeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">29. Although <hi>Monſieur Buſe,</hi> a French Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who read weekly a <hi>Lecture</hi> in Latin in his Chappel, by his French pronunciation and want of good delivery, did ſomewhat blemiſh the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the matter which he handled, yet the <hi>Arch-biſhops</hi> property ever was, to cheriſh and <hi>encourage</hi> him, and all others that preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and was never heard to give the <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> diſtaſt, but rather would commend, or excuſe him againſt other mens <hi>cenſures;</hi> ſaying, <q>If he were young, better experience would correct his defaults: and if he were in years, he was in that reſpect to be borne withall: alledging for both, that ſome would take exceptions ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, rather to ſatisfy their own too much cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, then for any juſt cauſe of diſlike in the Preacher.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30. As his continual endeavours were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:187791:31"/> thoſe of <hi>beſt</hi> gifts, and to encourage thoſe of <hi>meaner;</hi> ſo (as often as Church and State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affairs gave him leave) he was induſtrious in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding wholeſome Doctrine to the people, and a worthy <hi>pattern</hi> of true Divinity and diligence unto all others of the Clergy. When he was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> (unleſſe extraordinary buſineſſes of the <hi>Marches of Wales</hi> hinder'd him) he never failed to <hi>preach</hi> upon every Lords-day; many times riding five or ſix miles to a <hi>Pariſh-Church,</hi> and after Sermon came home to dinner. The like he did alſo when he was <hi>Arch-biſhop,</hi> and lay at <hi>Croydon,</hi> the Queen being in her Progreſſe. No Sunday eſcaped him in <hi>Kent,</hi> where the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen would exceedingly reſort unto him: and he would often preach ſo early in the morning in ſome <hi>Pariſh-Church,</hi> both in <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that he came afterwards to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the <hi>Cathedral-Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">31. His gift that way was excellent, as if you had heard Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf, or ſome of the ancient Biſhops in the primitive Church: his <hi>geſture</hi> and action in the Pulpit ſo grave and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, his <hi>words</hi> coming from him ſo fatherly and comely, and though plainly (for the moſt part) and without affectation, yet alwayes elegantly, with ſpecial choice, and ſubſtantial matter, full of good and ſound learning; plentifull in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities out of Scripture, Fathers and Schoolmen,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:187791:31"/> ſo ſingularly applied, that he much affected his Auditory therewith. And his <hi>pious life</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his religious Sentences. He never preached, but he firſt wrote his notes in <hi>Latin,</hi> and afterward kept them during his life. <q>For he would ſay, that whoſoever took that pains before his preaching, the older he waxed, the better he ſhould diſcharge that duty; but if he truſted only to his memory, his <hi>preaching</hi> in time would become <hi>pratling.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="32">32. When he was Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> he did much good alſo by his often <hi>conference</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> whom he uſed with mild and temperate ſpeeches, and thereby got many of them to conform themſelves, both Gentlemen and others: whereby, as at his firſt coming he found many <hi>Recuſants,</hi> ſo he left very few at his coming thence. Immediately after he came to be <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop,</hi> he convented before him the chiefeſt, and moſt learned <hi>Recuſants</hi> throughout all <hi>England:</hi> He alſo wrote letters to the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> his brethren, within the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to proceed with the <hi>Recuſants</hi> by their Authority Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and <hi>cenſures</hi> of the Church, and called yearly upon them for an account of their doings.</p>
            <p n="33">33. An. 1600. In the time of <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> ſent threeſcore men well armed to ſhew themſelves before the <hi>Court:</hi> of whoſe arrival Secretary <hi>Cecil,</hi> with the reſt of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:187791:32"/> Lords of the Council were right glad, and ſaid <hi>He was a moſt worthy Prelate.</hi> They had ſpeedily a leader appointed them, and marched preſently, and were the firſt that entred into the Gates of <hi>Eſſex houſe:</hi> and in the firſt Court made good the place untill the Earl yeelded himſelf, and was by the Lord <hi>Admiral</hi> brought to <hi>Lambeth houſe,</hi> where he remained an hour or two, and was from thence conveyed to the <hi>Tower.</hi> The Arch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>biſhop had like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe in readineſſe fourty Horſe-men well appointed, and expected directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Court, how to diſpoſe of them. The next morning, he ſent a Gentleman to know how the <hi>Queen</hi> did, and how ſhe reſted all night. To whom ſhe made Anſwer, <hi>That ſhe rested and ſlept the better for his care the day before: but I beſhrew his heart</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>he would not believe this of</hi> Eſſex, <hi>though I had often told him, it would, one day, thus come to paſſe.</hi> But indeed, the <hi>Queens</hi> own recommendation of the <hi>Earl</hi> had wrought that good opinion of him in the <hi>Arch-biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1602. <hi>Mar.</hi> 24. dyed <hi>Queen Elizabeth.</hi> And although the <hi>Arch biſhop</hi> was much dejected and grieved for the loſſe of his dear Soveraign and <hi>Miſtreſs,</hi> who had ſo highly advanced him: yet he with the reſt of the Lords, repaired imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and after two hours ſitting in <hi>Council,</hi> about the penning of the <hi>Proclamation, He</hi> principally (as his place required) with a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:187791:32"/> cheerfull countenance, and the reſt of the <hi>Lords</hi> in like ſort, accompanying him, firſt at the <hi>Court gate</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> with the applauſe and unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able comfort of all the people, proclaimed her moſt rightfull Succeſſor, <hi>King James.</hi> Afterwards in like cheerfull ſort, the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Lords,</hi> trouped up to the <hi>Croſs</hi> in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> and there with like acclamation of the Lord Mayor and Citizens proclaimed him again. The People and Citizens took great comfort in the preſence of the <hi>Arch-biſhop,</hi> as if they nothing doubted, but that all went well for the State in that Council, among whom He was preſent.</p>
            <p n="35">35. Beſides the pains, which he took himſelf, many years, with a number of worthy <hi>young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen</hi> in reading to them thrice a day, he took into his houſe, beſides his <hi>Chaplains,</hi> divers of quality to inſtruct them in the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> and other Lectures of ſundry <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Languages;</hi> giving them good allowance and preferments o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, as occaſion was offered. And beſides the many <hi>poor Scholars,</hi> whom he kept in his houſe till he could provide for them, and prefer them, he alſo maintained divers in the Univerſity, at his own charge.</p>
            <p n="36">36. He kept alſo for the exerciſe of <hi>Military Diſcipline,</hi> a godly <hi>Armory,</hi> and a fair <hi>Stable</hi> of great Horſes: inſomuch as he was able to arme at all points both horſe and foot, and divers times
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:187791:33"/> had one hundred foot, and fifty horſe of his own ſervants muſtered and trayned: for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he entertained <hi>Captains,</hi> &amp;c. His houſe, for the <hi>Lectures</hi> and <hi>Scholaſtick exerciſes</hi> therein per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, might juſtly be accounted <hi>a little Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and in ſome reſpects ſuperiour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His Domeſtick <hi>Chaplains,</hi> both before and ſince his death, attained to the chiefeſt honours and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in our Church and Common-wealth; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Bancroft, Ravis, Barlow,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="37">37. He carried himſelf with great <hi>Reſolution</hi> and courage in the determination of Cauſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to his proper Cognizance. When a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> of good note told him once, that the <hi>Lords</hi> of the Council were of another opinion then his <hi>Grace: What telleſt thou me</hi> (ſaid the Arch-biſhop) <hi>of the Lords of the Council? I tell thee, they are in theſe Caſes to be adviſed by us, and not we by them.</hi> He would upon ſuch occaſions oftentimes ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his private friends, toward his later time: <hi>That two things did help much to make a man confident in good cauſes: namely,</hi> Orbitas &amp; Senectus: <hi>and</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>they ſteed me both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="38">38. He gave <hi>Audience</hi> unto <hi>Suitors</hi> twice a day, and afforded them ſet hours for their <hi>diſpatch:</hi> at which time, he would ſo courteouſly intreat them, giving ſo mild and gentle Anſwers, that even they that ſped not in their ſuits, did depart without diſcontentment. Wherein I may juſtly compare
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:187791:33"/> him unto <hi>Titus, qui neminem unquam à ſe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem dimiſit.</hi> He often feaſted the <hi>Clergy, Nobility,</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> of his Dioceſs and Neighbourhood: at <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> eſpecially, his <hi>Gates</hi> were alwayes open, and his <hi>Hall</hi> ſet twice or thrice over with ſtrangers. Every year, he entertained the <hi>Queen</hi> at one of his houſes (and ſome years twice or thrice) who beſides other favours, would bid him <hi>Farewell</hi> by the name of her <hi>Black Husband,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="39">39. His Charity is teſtifyed by that notable <hi>Monument,</hi> his <hi>Hoſpital</hi> of the bleſſed Trinity in <hi>Croydon,</hi> which he built very fair and Colledge-wiſe, for a Warden and eight and twenty Brothers and Siſters. He builded alſo near unto it a goodly <hi>free School,</hi> with a School-maſters houſe, allowing to the School-maſter twenty pounds by year for ever. And when he had finiſhed and done the whole work, he found himſelf <hi>no worſe in his eſtate,</hi> then when he firſt began, which he aſcribed unto the extraordinary bleſſing and goodneſſe of <hi>God.</hi> After which, when the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador (by whom he was reputed a <hi>peerleſſe Prelate</hi> for piety and learning,) enquiring what Books he had written, was told, He had only publiſhed certain Books in the Engliſh tongue, <hi>in defence of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Government,</hi> and that he had founded an Hoſpital and a School: The Embaſſador reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Profecto Hoſpitale ad ſublevandam paupertatem,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:187791:34"/> 
               <hi>&amp; Schola ad inſtruendam juventutem, ſunt optimi libri quos Archiepiſcopus conſcribere potuit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30. 1603. <hi>Ap.</hi> 28. He was the principal Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at the funeral of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> crowned and anointed King <hi>James</hi> Jul. 25. being viſited by his Majeſty in his ſickneſſe, ſpake to him ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in Latin, and by his laſt words, <hi>pro eccleſia Dei, pro eccleſia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ei,</hi> was conceived by the King to commend unto his royal care (as he had done ſundry times before) the Church of <hi>England. Ob. ult. Feb. hora</hi> 8. <hi>pomerid. An. Dom.</hi> 1603. <hi>Aet.</hi> 73.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>M. Richard Hooker. <hi>Author of the Bookes of</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Politye.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="biography">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:187791:35"/>
            <head>V. Mr <hi>RICHARD HOOKER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his life, written by the R. R. Biſhop of</hi> Exeter, <hi>Dr</hi> Gauden.</head>
            <p n="1">1. HE was born in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> either in, or not far from the City of <hi>Exeter, An.</hi> 1550. (A Country that is, as Mr <hi>Cambden</hi> obſerves, <hi>ferax ingeniorum.)</hi> But with what preſages of his future eminency, there is not any notice to be had. One of his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles,</hi> was Chamberlain of <hi>Exeter,</hi> in Mr <hi>Hookers</hi> Youth, and contributed both care and coſt toward his Education in the free School there. His <hi>Parents</hi> need no other monument of honour, then this, that they were bleſſed with ſo <hi>worthie</hi> a Son.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This excellent Perſon had a <hi>body and ſoul</hi> every way ſo adjuſted and ſuited to each other, that they were like meet pairs happily married together, and living peaceably. His outward aſpect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:187791:36"/> and <hi>carriage</hi> was rather comely than Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly, his looks alwaies grave and reſerved: his ſoul more looking inward then exſpatiating at his eyes, or taking the outward proſpect of his ſenſes. He went alwaies, as if he meditated ſome great and good <hi>deſign:</hi> what he deſigned he induſtriouſly acted, without affectation or oſtentation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His <hi>words</hi> were alwaies ſober and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered: not more in number, then weight. He was like an <hi>hive</hi> full of honey, of a plain out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and a narrow acceſſe and orifice, but heavy, as having in him all manner of good literatute, induſtriouſly gathered and aptly digeſted. His <hi>friends</hi> or Confidents were <hi>few,</hi> but <hi>choiſe,</hi> as one that had no great opinion of himſelf, nor ſought the applauſe of others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. While he continued in <hi>Corpus Chriſti Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> few men of any note in either Univerſity, but promiſed more than he did, as to any great and publick undertaking: not that he wanted a publick ſpirit, or excellent Abilities in nature and education: but he was ſo locked up and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by a <hi>natural modeſtie,</hi> and <hi>ſelf-diſtruſt,</hi> that he ſeemed to think it reward ſufficient to have the conſcience of weldoing, and pleaſure enough, to ſee himſelf dayly profit in his ſtudies; and preferment even to envy, to enjoy vertue, though never ſo cloiſtred and confined to his own breaſt.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:187791:36"/> 5. Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> did not look upon the eaſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uietneſſe of a <hi>Colledge life,</hi> as the ultimate deſign of his ſtudies: nor did he ſay with the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, It is good to be here,</hi> as in a ſettled Tabernacle; but gently embraced thoſe ſmall offers of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Employments in the <hi>Country,</hi> which were made to him, by ſuch as thought them ſomewhat proportionate, if not to his worth and learning, yet to that humble plainneſſe and ſimplicity of his <hi>Genius</hi> and mode of living. His firſt living was <hi>Boſcomb</hi> in the Weſt, to which the <hi>Colledge</hi> preſented him: his next in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> called <hi>Drayton Beauchamp, An.</hi> 1584.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oiſe, which ſome <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> made, kept this good Country Parſon awake; who, however he could bear with patience and ſilence the reproaches caſt upon himſelf as a private man, yet he thought it <hi>ſtupor</hi> to hear, without juſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, his <hi>Mother</hi> reviled by ungrateful chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Hence ſprang that excellent work of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Politie.</hi> Wherein, he hath juſtly obtained this <hi>Encomium</hi> from all intelligent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <q>That never any man undertook a better cauſe (ſince the antient conflicts of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)</hi> nor handled it with an honeſter heart, an abler judgment, or an eloquenter ſtile.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. His firſt <hi>five Books</hi> he lived to publiſh: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in time brought forth thoſe eſteemed Abortive, the <hi>three</hi> laſt <hi>Books,</hi> with ſuch linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:187791:37"/> of their fathers virtue and vigour on them, that they may be eaſily and juſtly owned for <hi>genuin:</hi> although they had not the laſt politure of their Parents hand: The <hi>ſeventh</hi> book, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the writing of it with other indiſputable papers, or known <hi>Manuſcripts</hi> of Mr <hi>Hooker</hi>'s, is undoubtedly his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n hand throughout: The <hi>eighth</hi> is written by another hand (as a Copy) but interlined in many places with Mr <hi>Hooker</hi>'s own characters, as owned by him.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>An.</hi> 1592. He had the <hi>Dignities</hi> of a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend</hi> in <hi>Salisburie</hi> and the <hi>Subdeanrie</hi> beſtowed on him: and by the <hi>Queen</hi> he was preferred to be <hi>Maſter of the Temple,</hi> i. e. the publick preacher in that great Auditory, which requires an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent preacher, and where he may well deſerve an honourable maintenance. Mr <hi>Travers</hi> was popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly choſen by the <hi>Societie</hi> to be <hi>Lecturer</hi> in the afternoon, a man of eſteemed piety and good learning, but a <hi>Non-conformiſt.</hi> In compariſon of whom, Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> was much undervalued by the <hi>vulgar hearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Theſe two, although they differed in ſome matters, yet they correſponded in the main of ſound <hi>Doctrine</hi> and holy <hi>life:</hi> like generous <hi>rivals,</hi> they honoured and loved what they ſaw good in one another. Hence that very worthy ſpeech of Mr <hi>Travers,</hi> when being asked, what he thought of ſome vile aſperſion caſt upon Mr <hi>Hooker;</hi> he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:187791:37"/> anſwered, <hi>In truth, I take Mr Hooker to be a very holy man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>An.</hi> 1594. He was removed to his laſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Biſhopsburn</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and was made alſo <hi>Prebend</hi> of <hi>Canterburie</hi> by the favour of the Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> whoſe valiant and able <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> he was in that Conflict, which he ſo notably maintained againſt the Diſciplinarian faction, or the <hi>unruly Non-conformiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. This was the period of Mr <hi>Hooker</hi>'s pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, much below indeed his <hi>merit,</hi> but <hi>ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate,</hi> it ſeems, to the retiredneſſe of his <hi>temper,</hi> and moſt ſuitable to the policies of thoſe times, where <hi>Church-Governors</hi> were to be rather active than contemplative ſpirits. And from this ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing riſing, but not very high ground, did this excellent perſon take his aſcent and riſe to <hi>heaven, the onely preferment worthie of him,</hi> dying with great comfort at his parſonage in <hi>Kent</hi> about 50 years old, <hi>An.</hi> 1599, ſaies Mr <hi>Camden, An.</hi> 1603, ſaies his Monument. He was interred in the Chancel of <hi>Biſhopsbourn,</hi> where a fair Marble and Alabaſter Monument (no way violated or deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all our late years of confuſion) was long after erected to his Memory, <hi>An.</hi> 1634. <hi>See the rest in the eloquent Biſhop, before the Eccl. Pol.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="additions">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:187791:38"/>
               <head>ADDITIONS.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Out of Dr</hi> W. Covel's <hi>Defence of</hi> Hooker, 1603.</head>
               <p n="12">12. A <hi>Letter</hi> (which is here anſwered) was publiſhed by certain Proteſtants (as they term themſelves) which I hear (how true I know not) is tranſlated into other tongues: This they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume hath given that wound, to that reverend and learned man, that it was not the leaſt cauſe to procure his death. But it is far otherwiſe: for he contemned it in his <hi>wiſdom</hi> (as it was fit) and yet in his <hi>humilitie</hi> would have anſwered it, if he had lived.—But firſt of all he was loth to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with ſo weak adverſaries, thinking it <hi>unfit</hi> (as himſelf ſaid) <hi>that a man that hath a long jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ſhould turn back to beat every barking curre;</hi> and having taken it in hand, his urgent and greater affairs, together with the want of ſtrength, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with much labour, would not give him time to ſee it finiſhed.—Death hath taken from us a ſweet <hi>friend,</hi> a wiſe <hi>Counſellour,</hi> and a ſtrong <hi>Champion.</hi> Others are fit enough to live in the midſt of errour, vanitie, unthankfulneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, but he was too good. p. 13.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:187791:38"/> 13. As, profoundly to <hi>judge</hi> with ſound vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of all learning, was common to him with divers others; ſo, to <hi>expreſſe</hi> what he conceived, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eloquence of a moſt pure ſtile, was the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city almoſt of himſelf alone. That honourable Knight Sr <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> gave a taſt in an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Recreation,</hi> how well that ſtyle would befit an Argument of a <hi>graver Subject:</hi> which it may be is more unpleaſing in the taſt of ſome, becauſe the manner is learned, and the ſubject is not agreeing to their <hi>humour.</hi> Doubtleſſe the perfecting of a <hi>ſtyle,</hi> and eſpecially of our <hi>Engliſh ſtyle</hi> (which, in my opinion, refuſeth not the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ornaments of any language) hath many mo helps, than thoſe honourable places of learning, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> can afford. And therefore in thoſe things which they conceive (and ſome of them conceive much) there are found in the Princes <hi>Court,</hi> divers moſt purely eloquent, whom even the beſt in the <hi>Univerſities</hi> may deſpair to imitate. And (if I may ſpeak without offence) I am fully perſwaded, that Mr <hi>Hookers ſtile</hi> (if he had had leſſe learning: a ſtrange fault: for the weight of his learning made it too heavy) had been incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the <hi>beſt</hi> that ever was written in our Church. If our <hi>Engliſh ſtorie</hi> had been born to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>appi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ever to have been attired in ſuch rich orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhe might worthily have bin entertained in the beſt Courts that the World hath. But all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:187791:39"/> know our actions have been better done, then they have been told.</p>
               <p n="14">14. His Arguments, you ſay, are found in the Anſwer of that <hi>Reverend Father</hi> unto Mr <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright.</hi> If there were no difference, yet the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> of their Arguments were reaſon enough for you to allow Mr <hi>Hooker,</hi> ſeeing you h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve given your approbation of the works of that <hi>moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father:</hi> (whoſe worthineſſe, no doubt, can receive little honour from your praiſe:) yet you know, that the whole ſubject of Mr <hi>Hooker</hi>'s firſt <hi>four</hi> Books, is an argument, as, full of learning, ſo directly heretofore not handled by any, that I know. Concerning thoſe <hi>three</hi> Books of his, which from his own mouth I am informed that they were <hi>finiſht,</hi> I know not in whoſe hands they are, nor whether the Church ſhall be bettered by ſo excellent a work. For; as the Church might have been happy, if he had lived to have written more, ſo ſhe were not altogether ſo much harmed, if ſhe might but enjoy, what he hath written. p. 150.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The government of his <hi>paſſions</hi> was in his own power, and he was able to rule them. For he was truly of a <hi>mild</hi> ſpirit, and an <hi>humble</hi> heart; and abounding in all other virtues. Yet he ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally excelled in the grace of <hi>Meekneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Gravitie</hi> of his looks, was cleered by thoſe that did ſit or converſe with him; leaſt he ſhould be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:187791:39"/> burdenſome unto them; but a full laughter few ever diſcovered in him. Some ſuch our church had in all ages, a few now <hi>alive,</hi> which are her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, if ſhe can uſe them well, but more that are <hi>dead,</hi> whom ſhe ought to praiſe. For all theſe were <hi>honourable men in their generations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>* While this was under the Printers hand, I had the happineſſe to be in Dr <hi>Pococks</hi> company, (ſometimes Fellow of <hi>C. C. C.)</hi> and heard him, amongſt other good Diſcourſe, tell a ſtory of <hi>Hooker</hi> to this effect: That <hi>He,</hi> with ſome others of the colledge, journeying <hi>on foot</hi> (as the manner then was) into their country, by the way viſited Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> (ſometime of the ſame Coll.) The <hi>Biſhop</hi> underſtanding ſome <hi>Scholars</hi> deſired to ſee him, (or as we now ſpeak more courtly) to wait upon his Lordſhip; ſaid, <hi>They ſhould be welcome.</hi> It was added, <hi>They were of</hi> Corpus Chriſti: <hi>They ſhall be the more wellcome to me,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Biſhop.</hi> To omit the reſt of their entertainment, when the <hi>Scholars</hi> took their leave, the <hi>Biſhop</hi> gave them, every one a <hi>viaticum,</hi> ſome money to bear their charges, and eſpecially to <hi>Hooker:</hi> upon whom alſo, he pleaſantly ſaid, he would beſtow <hi>his own Nag,</hi> and brought forth, and gave him an old <hi>ſtaff,</hi> which had been <hi>his</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in his <hi>Travel.—Te nunc habet iſte ſecundum.</hi> Had <hi>I</hi> that <hi>ſtaff, I</hi> ſhould eſteem it no leſſe than a very Sacred <hi>Relique.</hi>*</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="biography">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:187791:40"/>
            <head>VI. Dr. <hi>LANCELOT ANDREWES</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his Funeral Sermon by</hi> John <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Ely.</head>
            <p n="1">1. HE was born in the City of <hi>London,</hi> of honeſt and godly Parents; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his breeding in learning, left him a ſufficient <hi>Patrimony</hi> and inheritance, which is deſcended to his heir, at <hi>Rawreth</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His life was well compoſed and ordered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from his <hi>child-hood.</hi> In his tendereſt years, he ſhewed ſuch readineſſe and ſharpneſſe of wit and capacity, that his two firſt Maſters (Mr. <hi>Ward</hi> and Mr. <hi>Mulcaſter)</hi> contended for him, who ſhould have the honour of his breeding, that after became the honour of their Schools, and all Learning.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The right reverend Father in God Lancelot, Biſhop of Wincheſter, and Praelate of the Garter.</head>
               <p>Vaughan ſculp.</p>
            </figure>
            <p n="4">4. Their pains and care he ſo carefully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred all his life long, that he ſtudied alwaies how to do good to them and theirs. In which grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe he promoted Dr. <hi>Ward</hi> to the Parſonage of <hi>Waltham:</hi> and ever loved and honoured his Maſter <hi>Mulcaſter</hi> during his life; and was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual helper to <hi>him</hi> and his <hi>Son.</hi> And as if he had made Mr. <hi>Mulcaſter</hi> his Tutor or Superviſor, he placed his <hi>picture</hi> over the door of his <hi>ſtudy:</hi> whereas in all the reſt of the houſe you could ſcantly ſee a picture.</p>
            <p n="5">5. From Mr. <hi>Mulcaſter</hi> he went to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> to <hi>Pembroke Hall,</hi> and was there admitted one of Dr. <hi>Wats Scholars:</hi> (a notable <hi>Grammari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> well entred in the <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> tongues, and likewiſe in <hi>Geometry,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Mathematicks:)</hi> and after, a <hi>Fellow</hi> there, in which he paſſed over all <hi>Degrees</hi> and places in ſuch ſort, that he ever ſeemed worthy of higher, and would in the end attain the higheſt: for his abilities and vertues were mature and ripe for greater employments.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He often lamented that he never could find a fit opportunity to ſhew his thankfulneſſe to Dr.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:187791:42"/> 
               <hi>Wats,</hi> his Patron, nor to any of his Poſterity. Yet he did not utterly forget him in his will, having ordered that the <hi>two Fellowſhips</hi> to be founded by him in <hi>Pembroke-Hall,</hi> ſhould alwaies be choſen and filled, out of the Scholars of Dr. <hi>Wats</hi> Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation (if they were found fit) of which himſelf had been one.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Being in holy <hi>Orders,</hi> he attended the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and zealous <hi>Henry Earl of Huntington,</hi> Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>York,</hi> and was employed by him in often preaching and conference with Recuſants, both of the Clergy and Laity: In which God ſo bleſt his endeavours that he converted many.</p>
            <p n="8">8. After this Mr. Secretary <hi>Walſingham</hi> takes notice of him, and obtained him of the Earl, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his preferment, in which he would never permit him to take any <hi>Country-benefice,</hi> leſt he and his great learning ſhould be buried in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Church. His intent was to make him <hi>Reader of Controverſies</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and for his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance he aſſigned to him (as I am informed) the leaſe of the Parſonage of <hi>Alton</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire:</hi> which after his death he returned to his Lady; which ſhe never knew or thought of.</p>
            <p n="9">9. After this he obtained the <hi>Vicaridge of S. Giles</hi> without <hi>Creeple-gate, London,</hi> and a <hi>Prebend</hi> Reſidentiaries place in <hi>Pauls,</hi> and was choſen <hi>Maſter</hi> of <hi>Pembroke-Hall,</hi> and afterward was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the <hi>Deanry of Weſtminſter:</hi> and all this
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:187791:42"/> without any ambition or ſuite of his own, being promoted for his great worth.</p>
            <p n="10">10. His knowledge in the learned and modern <hi>Tongues,</hi> to the number of <hi>fifteen</hi> in all (as I am informed) was admirable: His <hi>Memory</hi> great: His <hi>Judgment</hi> profound: His pains and <hi>Induſtry</hi> was infinite. In the works he wrote, he uſed no man to read for him (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others employed whole Colledges to read and ſtudy for them:) he only uſed an <hi>Amanuenſis,</hi> to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe that, which himſelf had firſt written with his own hand.</p>
            <p n="11">11. As he was himſelf moſt learned, ſo he was a ſingular lover and encourager of <hi>Learned men:</hi> which appeareth in his liberality and bounty to Mr. <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cluverius,</hi> Mr. <hi>Voſſius,</hi> Mr. <hi>Grotius,</hi> Mr. <hi>Erpenius,</hi> whom he attempted with the offer of a very large ſtipend out of his own purſe to draw into <hi>England,</hi> to have read and taught the <hi>Oriental Tongues</hi> here.</p>
            <p n="12">12. When the Biſhopricks of <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Saliſbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> were void, and ſome things were to be pared from them, ſome overture being made to him to take them, he refuſed them utterly: He ſeemed to anſwer, <hi>Nolo epiſcopari, quia nolo alienare:</hi> I will not be made a Biſhop, becauſe I will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate Biſhops Lands.</p>
            <p n="13">13. After this, by ſome perſwaſion, he accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Chicheſter;</hi> yet with ſome fear of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:187791:43"/> and after that, of <hi>Eli:</hi> and laſt of this of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> (Whence God hath tranſlated him to Heaven.) In which he freed himſelf and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of a Penſion of 400 <hi>per an.</hi> Which many of his Predeceſſors had paid. He was <hi>Almoner, Dean</hi> of the Chappel, and a <hi>privy Counſellor</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles:</hi> In which he ſpake and meddled little in <hi>Civil</hi> and temporal Affairs, being out of his profeſſion and element: but in cauſes of the <hi>Church</hi> he ſpake fully and home.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Whereſoever he lived, all places were better'd by his providence and goodneſſe. S. <hi>Giles</hi> was reduced by him to a <hi>Rate</hi> toward the better maintenance of the place, and the houſe repaired. He found nothing in the Treaſury in <hi>Pembroke-Hall:</hi> he left it in ready mony a thouſand pound: being Prebend Reſidentiary in <hi>Pauls,</hi> he built the houſe in <hi>Creed-Lane</hi> belonging to his Prebend, and recovered it to the Church: he repaired the Dean's lodging. When he came to <hi>Chicheſter</hi> he repaired the Palace there: at <hi>Eli,</hi> he ſpent on the Biſhops houſes two thouſand pound. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he refuſed to make ſome Leaſes in his laſt years, which might have been very beneficial to him, for the good of his Succeſſor. His reaſon was, <hi>Many are too ready to ſpoil Biſhopricks, and few enough to uphold them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. He was alwaies a diligent and painfull <hi>Preacher:</hi> moſt of his <hi>Solemn Sermons</hi> he was moſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:187791:43"/> carefull of, and exact; I dare ſay, few of them, but they paſſed his hand and were thrice <hi>reviſed,</hi> before they were <hi>preached:</hi> and he ever miſliked often and looſe preaching, without ſtudy of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: and he would be bold with himſelf and ſay, <hi>When he preached twice a day at S.</hi> Giles, <hi>he prated once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. After he came to have an Epiſcopal Houſe with a Chappel, he kept <hi>monthly Communions</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably; yea though himſelf had received at the Court, the ſame month. In which, his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was not only decent and religious, but alſo exemplary. He ever <hi>offer'd twice</hi> at the Altar, and ſo did every one of his ſervants: to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he gave them mony, leſt it ſhould be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to them.</p>
            <p n="17">17. He was ſuch an enemy to <hi>Simony,</hi> that he endured many Troubles by <hi>Quare impedit,</hi> and <hi>Duplex querela.</hi> As for himſelf, he ſeldome gave a Benefice or Preferment to him that <hi>petition'd</hi> for it: he rather <hi>ſent</hi> for men of note, that he thought wanted preferment, and gave them Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends and Benefices, under Seal, before they knew of it; as to Mr. <hi>Boys</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fuller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> he did abhor, as one principal cauſe among many, of the forrein and civil Wars in Chriſtendom, and invaſion of the Turk. And at home, he wiſhed ſome man would take the pains <hi>to collect,</hi> how many <hi>Families,</hi> that were
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:187791:44"/> raiſed by the ſpoils of the <hi>Church</hi> are now vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the place thereof knows them no more.</p>
            <p n="19">19. He was a great <hi>Almes-giver.</hi> When he liv'd at St. <hi>Giles,</hi> his certain Almes there was <hi>ten pound per an.</hi> paid quarterly by equal portions: and <hi>twelve pence</hi> every Sunday he came to Church and <hi>five ſhillings</hi> at every Communion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The total of his pious and charitable works mentioned in his will, amounts to the ſum of <hi>ſix thouſand three hundred twenty ſix pound:</hi> He gave in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Alms in ſome few years before his death, to the ſum of <hi>one thouſand three hundred and forty pound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. A great part of <hi>five hours</hi> every day did he ſpend in <hi>prayer</hi> and devotion to God: and a good while before he ſickned he ſpent all his time in prayer: and in the time of his ſickneſſe he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually prayed, until it pleaſed God to receive his bleſſed Soul to himſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:44"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:45"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lo here a</hi> Prelate, <hi>in whom</hi> Light, <hi>&amp;</hi> Heate</l>
                     <l>Learning &amp; Zeale, Meekneſse, &amp; Courage <hi>met,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In</hi> Gods <hi>cauſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>:</hi> Kings, <hi>our</hi> Brownrige <hi>was</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> Boanerges, <hi>though a</hi> Barnabas.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>W: Faithorne ſculp.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="biography">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:187791:45"/>
            <head>VII. <hi>RALPH BRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NRIG Biſhop of</hi> Exeter.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of Doctor</hi> Gauden's <hi>Sermon at his Funeral.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. BIſhop <hi>Brounrig</hi> was a perſon of that ſoundneſſe of <hi>Judgment,</hi> of that conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity for an unſpotted <hi>life,</hi> of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſpected <hi>Integrity,</hi> that his life was <hi>virtutism nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> (as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Nepotian) Ita in ſingulis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus eminebat, quaſi caeteras non habuiſſet:</hi> ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent in every good and perfect gift, as if he had had but one onely. I never heard of any thing ſaid by him, which <hi>a wiſe and good man</hi> would have wiſhed unſaid or undone; yet I had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to know him above thirty years.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſpring of this ſo fair, ſo deep, ſo clear, ſo noble a ſtream of Learning, Piety and Wiſdom, was at <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> a Town of good note in <hi>Suffolk:</hi> where he was born <hi>An.</hi> 1592. His parents of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:187791:46"/> condition, of worthy reputation, and of very Chriſtian Converſation. When he was not many weeks old, God took away his earthly <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that himſelf might have the more tender care of the <hi>Orphan.</hi> By the prudence of his pious <hi>Mother,</hi> his Youth and firſt years of reaſon were carefully improved for his breeding in all good Learning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He was ſent in his fourteenth year to <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> There, his Modeſty, Pregnancy and Piety ſoon invited <hi>preferment.</hi> He was firſt made <hi>Scholar</hi> of the Houſe, and after <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> a little ſooner then either his years or ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in rigour of <hi>Statute</hi> permitted: but the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> was impatient not to make ſure of him, by grafting him firmly into that Society, which had been famous for many excellent men, but for none more then <hi>Brounrig.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. When King <hi>James</hi> (that moſt learned Prince) was pleas'd to honour the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> by his preſence, and to make <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes</hi> of Scholars the beſt part of his Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this perſon (then a young man) was one of thoſe who were choſen by the Univerſity to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn that Reception of the <hi>King.</hi> The part he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed was <hi>Jocoſerious</hi> (of <hi>praevaricator)</hi> a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Philoſophy with Wit and Oratory. This he diſcharged, to the <hi>admiration</hi> more then the <hi>mirth</hi> of the King, and the other learned Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:187791:46"/> who rejoyced to ſee ſuch a luxuriancy of <hi>Wit</hi> was conſiſtent with <hi>innocency;</hi> that jeſting was confined to conveniency, and <hi>Mirth</hi> married with that <hi>Modeſty</hi> which became the <hi>Muſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Among his learned and accurate performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in publick, I cannot but obſerve, that when he took the Degree of B. D. the Text upon which he choſe to preach his <hi>Latin Sermon</hi> was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and preparatory to his after ſufferings: <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 29. <hi>Vobis autem datum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>To you it is given on the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe in him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> Which eloquent and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sermon he afterwards was to fulfill indeed. <hi>Quod docuit verbo, firmavit exemplo:</hi> He made his Doctrin good by his practice, taking up the croſs of Chriſt and following him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He was preferred to be <hi>Prebend</hi> of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiate Church of <hi>Eli,</hi> by the favour and love of the then Biſhop of that Seat, Doctor <hi>Felton,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry holy and good man. He had alſo a good living at <hi>Barlow,</hi> not far from <hi>Cambridge,</hi> a Country Village; where he condiſcended in his <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>catechiſing</hi> to ordinary capacities: (He oft deplored the diſuſe and want of Catechiſing:) After that, this great Lamp was ſet and ſhined in a Sphere more proper and proportionate, being choſen <hi>Maſter of Katharine Hall.</hi> Here, it was wonderfull to ſee, how the <hi>Buildings,</hi> the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues,</hi> the <hi>Students</hi> and the ſtudiouſneſs of that place
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:187791:47"/> increaſed, by the care, counſell, prudence, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Fame of Doctor <hi>Brounrig;</hi> who had ſuch an eye to all, that he overſaw none, frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Studies, and examining even younger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cholars, that they might be encouraged in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Piety.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He kept up very much, as good Learning and good Manners, ſo the honour of <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divinity, and orderly <hi>Conformity:</hi> He kept to the Doctrin, Worſhip, Devotion, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Church of England: Which,</hi> he would ſay, <hi>he liked better and better, as he grew older.</hi> If any, out of ſcruple or tenderneſſe of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> was leſſe ſatisfied with ſome things, no man had a more tender <hi>heart,</hi> or a gentler <hi>hand</hi> to heal them. He would <hi>convince,</hi> though he did not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> Gain-ſayers; and if he could not perſwade them, yet he would pity and pray for them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He could endure <hi>differences</hi> among learned and godly men, in opinions, eſpecially ſublime and obſcure, without diſtance in affection. He thought that <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf was in ſome points left unto us leſſe clear and poſitive, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans might have wherewith to exerciſe both <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> in themſelves, and <hi>Charity</hi> towards others. He very much venerated the firſt worthy <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> of Religion at home and abroad: yet was he not ſo addicted to any <hi>one</hi> Maſter, as not freely to uſe his own great and mature Judgment. He
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:187791:47"/> hoped every good Man had his <hi>Retractations,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>actual</hi> or <hi>intentional;</hi> though all had no time to write them, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> did. He had the greateſt <hi>Antipathy</hi> againſt thoſe unquiet and prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Spirits, which affect endleſſe Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Varieties and Novelties in Religion, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on a party, and under that skreen of Religion to advance their private <hi>Interests</hi> and politick Deſigns.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> though he needed a ſet form as little as any, yet he had a particular great eſteem of it: 1. For the honour and piety of its Martyrly <hi>Compoſers:</hi> 2. For its excellent <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and prudent <hi>Method:</hi> 3. For the <hi>good</hi> he ſaw it did to all ſober Chriſtians: the want of which he ſaw was not ſupplied by any Miniſters <hi>private</hi> way of praying and preaching. Not, that the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> is unalterable: but he judged all ſuch Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations ought to be done by the <hi>publick ſpirit.</hi> As for <hi>Biſhops,</hi> he was too learned a man to doubt, and too honeſt to deny the univerſal <hi>Custom and practice</hi> of the Church of Chriſt, in all ages and places for fifteen hundred years, according to the <hi>pattern</hi> (at leaſt) received from the <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> who, without doubt, followed, as they beſt knew, the mind of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. He was by the favour of King <hi>Charls,</hi> and to the great liking of all good men made Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> Anno 1641. Whereupon, a certain
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:187791:48"/> Gentleman told me; He wondred Doctor <hi>Broun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig</hi> would be made a Biſhop, whom he had heard ſometime declare his judgment againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> Which, as I no way beleived, ſo relating it ſoon after to the Biſhop, He with ſome paſſion replyed; <hi>I never thought, much leſſe ſaid, as that perſon hath falſely averred. I thank God, I took the office of a Biſhop with a good Conſcience, and ſo I hope by his Mercy I ſhall both maintain and diſcharge it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. And however this excellent Biſhop enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the benefit of the Kings favour and muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, as to his Biſhoprick, or any other prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, after the <hi>Troubles</hi> of the times; yet he was ever moſt unmovable in his royal reſpects of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, gratitude, love and obedience. According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when <hi>O. P.</hi> with ſome ſhew of reſpect to him, demanded his judgment in ſome publick affairs, the Biſhop with his wonted Gravity and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome replyed: <hi>My Lord, the beſt Counſel I can give you, is that of our Saviour, Render unto Caeſar the things that be Caeſars, and unto God the things that be Gods.</hi> With which free Anſwer <hi>O. P.</hi> reſted rather ſilenced then ſatisfyed.</p>
            <p n="12">12. This Grave perſonage, when forced to retire, was uſefull to thoſe that were worthy of him, and knew how to value and uſe him, either as a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or as a <hi>Divine,</hi> or a <hi>Counſellor,</hi> or a <hi>Comforter,</hi> or a <hi>Friend.</hi> Among thoſe, that gave him a liberal and noble entertainment, <hi>Thomas</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:187791:48"/> 
               <hi>Rich</hi> Eſq; of <hi>Sunning</hi> in <hi>Bark-ſhire,</hi> deſerves with honour to be thus regiſtred, <hi>That he was the ſpecial friend to Biſhop</hi> Brounrig. Indeed none could be hoſpitable to him <hi>gratis:</hi> He alwaies paid largely for his entertainments by his many excellent <hi>Diſcourſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. He was alwaies, when in health, as cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (as far as the <hi>Tragedies</hi> of the Times gave leave) as one that had the <hi>continual feaſt</hi> of a good Conſcience; and as content, as if he had had a Lords eſtate. All diminutions and indignities, which ſome men put upon ſo worthy and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a perſon, he digeſted into patience and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Thus he was in ſome degree conformable to the <hi>primitive Biſhops,</hi> which were poor and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, yea to the great Biſhop of our Souls, <hi>Who for our ſakes made himſelf of no reputation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. About a year before he dyed, he was invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with much reſpect and civility to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Societies of both <hi>Temples,</hi> to bleſſe them, as with his conſtant Reſidence, ſo with his Fatherly <hi>Inſtructions and Prayers.</hi> To ſhew the Reality of their love and value to his Lordſhip, they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allowed an annual honorary Recompence to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their Thanks, but they provided handſome Lodgings, and furniſhed them with all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, convenient and comely for a perſon of his worth. Such as could hear him preach rejoyced at his gracious words: ſuch as for the crowd could
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:187791:49"/> not come nigh enough to hear him, had pleaſure to ſtay and behold him, conceiving they ſaw <hi>a Sermon in his looks,</hi> and were better'd by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Aſpect of ſo worthy a perſon.</p>
            <p n="15">15. God was pleaſed to exerciſe him with bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily pains, indiſpoſitions and diſtempers, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with ſharp fits of the <hi>Stone;</hi> but under all theſe God ſupported him with his <hi>Grace,</hi> and ſpirit, as alwaies humble, devout and pious, ſo for the moſt part ſociable, ferene and cheerfull, till he had lived to his ſixty ſeventh year. He had more frequent Infirmities, as gentle <hi>monitors,</hi> a little before his death, of which he would ſpeak to my ſelf and others, as <hi>one that by dying dayly was well acquainted with death:</hi> and would ſay, <hi>That it was a very cheap time now to die: there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo little temptation to deſire life, and ſo many to welcome death: ſince he had lived to ſee no King in the State, no Biſhop in the Church, no Peer in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament worthy of that name.</hi> He only hoped and prayed that God would favour him ſo far with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as to let him dy without pain: as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he did. For after his ſpirits were in ten days decayed and waſted, he ſlumbred much, yet had vigilant Intervals; at which times he gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to prayer and meditation and holy Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: And being full of the Grace and peace of God, and confirmed in it by the <hi>Abſolution</hi> of the Church (which belongs to all that dye in the true
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:187791:49"/>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:187791:51"/> faith, and bleſſed hope of penitent ſinners) he placidly rendred his holy, devout and precious Soul to God that gave it, <hi>Dec.</hi> 7. 1659. <hi>vid. fin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. His <hi>Body</hi> for ſtature and figure was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what taller and bigger then ordinary, yet very comely. No man ever became the Preachers Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, or the Doctors Chair, or the Epiſcopal Seat (it was called of old <hi>Thronus Epiſcopalis)</hi> better then he did; carrying before him ſuch an unaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected State and grandeur, ſuch a benign gravity, and a kind of ſmiling Severity, that one might ſee much in him to be <hi>reverenced,</hi> and more to be <hi>loved:</hi> yet what was venerable in him was very <hi>amiable,</hi> and what was amiable was very <hi>venerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. If you pleaſe to add to your former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours (while he lived amongſt you) this laſt, of giving order and leave to adorn your <hi>Chappel</hi> with any <hi>Monument</hi> for him, you need be at no more coſt, then to inſcribe, on a <hi>plain Stone,</hi> the name of BISHOP BROUNRIG: This will make that Stone <hi>Marble</hi> enough, and your Chappel a <hi>Mauſoleum.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Naz. Orat.</hi> 23.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:50"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:50"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:51"/>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:187791:51"/>
            <head>VIII. Mr <hi>THO. GATAKER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Out of the Narrative annexed to his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermon.</head>
            <p n="1">1. HE was a branch of an antient Family, ſo firmly by Gods providence plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> that the ſtock hath continued in the ſame Houſe, carrying the name of its owner, and known by the title of <hi>Gata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre-hall,</hi> by an uninterrupted ſucceſſion from the time of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His <hi>Father</hi> was houſhold Chaplain to <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and Paſtor of S. <hi>Edmunds</hi> in <hi>Lumbardſtreet London.</hi> In that parſonage-houſe, by his Wife <hi>Margarit,</hi> being of an honeſt Family of the <hi>Pigots</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire,</hi> among other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he had this Son <hi>Thomas,</hi> born <hi>Septem.</hi> 4. 1574.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In his childhood, he was ſo addicted to learning, that he needed a <hi>bridle</hi> rather than a <hi>ſpur.</hi> This love of learning joyned with an admirable
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:187791:52"/> capacity, a nimble <hi>wit</hi> and vaſt <hi>memorie,</hi> adorned with ſober manners, advanced him from the Grammar School to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie,</hi> (where he was by his father placed in St <hi>John</hi>'s Colledge, in <hi>Cambridge)</hi> in the 15 year of his Age, 1590.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Here, not from mere <hi>favour,</hi> but from <hi>merit</hi> (upon proof of his learning) he was choſen <hi>Scholar</hi> of that worthy Society: wherein he continued his ſtudies with unwearyed diligence and happy ſucceſſe, till with abilities anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his Degree, he commenced <hi>Master of Arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Take for an inſtance of his Induſtry this: That he was a conſtant Auditor of that eminent light of learning Mr <hi>Jo. Boys:</hi> who read a <hi>Greek</hi> Lecture in his <hi>bed</hi> to certain young ſtudents, that preferred <hi>antelucana ſtudia</hi> before their reſt and eaſe. The <hi>Notes</hi> whereof he kept as a Treaſure, and being viſited by Mr <hi>Boys</hi> many years after, he produced them to the no ſmall joy of the good old man, who profeſſed himſelf made ſome years yonger by that entertainment.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Such eſteem he was of in the Univerſity, that he was choſen to be Fellow ef <hi>Sidney</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, while it was in building. Mean while, he retired to a Gentlemans houſe in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> where he expounded ſome part of Scripture every morning. At which exerciſe, Dr <hi>Stern,</hi> ſuffragan of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> at a time happening to be preſent, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:187791:52"/> approving his endowments, exhorted Mr <hi>Gataker</hi> to take holy <hi>Orders.</hi> But he well weighed the burden of that Calling, and modeſtly judging of his own Abilities, deferred the matter, till by the advice of Mr <hi>Alvey,</hi> formerly his <hi>Tutor,</hi> and by a ſecond inſtance of the Doctor, he aſſented to be Ordained by the ſaid <hi>Suffragan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Sidney</hi> Coll: being finiſhed, he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his ſtation there, and was happy in ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Young Students</hi> with principles of piety and learning. He was alſo a partner to ſome other <hi>charitable Divines,</hi> in a pious Deſign of preaching in places adjacent to the Univerſity, where need was. And for half a year he preached at <hi>Everton</hi> every Lords day.</p>
            <p n="8">8. After this, he removed from <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to Sr <hi>William Cooks</hi> Family, then reſident in <hi>London,</hi> where he made a more publick diſcovery of his Miniſterial gifts, and was invited to the Lecturers place in <hi>Lincolns Inne.</hi> But he, according to his uſual Modeſty declin'd it, till Dr <hi>Mountague,</hi> Mr of <hi>Sidney</hi> Coll. then in London, with an intention to cal Mr <hi>Gataker</hi> back to the College to read the <hi>Hebrew Lecture,</hi> laying that aſide, encouraged him againſt his own diffidence, and with his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Arguments wrought him at laſt to an Aſſent.</p>
            <p n="9">9. At <hi>Lincolns Inne</hi> he ſpent ten years to the advancement of piety: and in the <hi>Vacations</hi> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:187791:53"/> and preached in the Family of Sir <hi>William Cook;</hi> to whoſe Lady he was neer in blood: and ſo dear to both, that in conſideration of his pains freely taken, they ſetled upon Mr <hi>Gataker</hi> an Annuity of twenty pounds. This he enjoyed ſome few years, but after (for ſome reaſons) gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly <hi>remitted</hi> unto the Heir of that Family, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to uſe the right he had, and forbidding his Executour to claim any <hi>Arrears</hi> of that Annuity.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>An.</hi> 1611. being called to the Rectory of <hi>Redrith</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> commending his former charge to the Grace of God, he betook himſelf to the ſole attendance on that Flock of which God had now made him Overſeer. His <hi>Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie</hi> in diſcharge thereof was conſtant and great, notwithſtanding an almoſt perpetual <hi>head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach,</hi> wherewith God had exerciſed him from his very youth. To the work of his preaching on the <hi>Lords day,</hi> he added a weekly <hi>Catechetical</hi> Lecture on <hi>Friday</hi> in the Evening, which he continued, accurately and methodically, till he had gone through the whole <hi>bodie of Divinitie,</hi> and gave it over when he obſerved his pariſhoners grown to a neglect his of <hi>free labours</hi> in thatkind. <hi>Solent ultroneae putere merces.</hi> Hieron.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>An.</hi> 1620. Having a juſtifiable curioſity to ſee our neighbour Church in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> and ſomething of the other Provinces in <hi>Belgium,</hi> he took the advantage of the <hi>Truce</hi> then
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:187791:53"/> between the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and the <hi>Hollander,</hi> for a free paſſage between both Countries. In this travel he ſhewed himſelf a <hi>good preacher</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> at <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> and a <hi>good Diſputant</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Flanders.</hi> God proſpered his journey; and within a <hi>month,</hi> having viewed the moſt conſiderable places in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, he returned ſafe.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>An.</hi> 1643. Being ſcarce recover'd from a violent fit of the <hi>Collick,</hi> he was called into the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines:</hi> where his modeſt and peaceable behaviour was remarkable. During his attendance there, the Maſterſhip of <hi>Trinitie Col.</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> the greateſt preferment in that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, was offerd him. But this good man (though often importuned by many friends to accept of the motion) according to his accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Modeſty</hi> refuſed to undertake that place of much honour and advantage, pleading, together with his unworthineſſe, his old age and weakneſſe of body.</p>
            <p n="13">13. His Gifts of <hi>edification</hi> may be ſeen in his Works extant, <hi>viz. Of the Nature and Uſe of Lots. A volum of Sermons in fol. De Novi Teſt. ſtylo Diſſertatio. Comment. in M. Anton. Imp.</hi> and many more. His <hi>Polite literature</hi> was much eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by learned men abroad, <hi>Salmaſius</hi> and others, with whom he held correſpondence: And the exerciſe of it, with <hi>condeſcention</hi> to children, hath
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:187791:54"/> been admired at <hi>Tunbridge</hi> School in the Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. He had a felicity to make his human literature (as it ought to be) ſubſervient to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p n="14">14. His graces of <hi>Sanctification</hi> were alſo very eminent: His <hi>pietie,</hi> in the care of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and love to Gods Houſe: His <hi>Charitie,</hi> in his tender ſenſe of the Churches Afflictions, and abridging himſelf of his liberty in ſome law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things to pleaſe the weak: His <hi>Humilitie,</hi> in a low eſteem of his Abilities, and declining of dignities and preferments: His <hi>Meekneſſe,</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with the meaneſt, and deſcending to them in the way of Counſel and ſatisfaction of their doubts: His <hi>patience,</hi> in bearing the afflictions on his body; and his <hi>Faith,</hi> in commending his ſoul into the hands of God. <hi>Satur Vitae tanquam conviva receſſit.</hi> An. D. 1654. aet. 80.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>—He is gone,</l>
               <l>Learnd in all here, where more is to be known.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:54"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:55"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>D<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. HENRY HAMMOND,</hi> From an Original Picture in the Hall of Magdalene College, Oxford. Pub. 1 Nov. 1796. by E &amp; S<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Harding Pall Mall.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="biography">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:187791:55"/>
            <head>IX. Dr. <hi>H. HAMMOND.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his life written by Dr.</hi> John Fell, <hi>Dean of</hi> Ch. Ch.</head>
            <p>HE was born in <hi>Surrey,</hi> 18. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1605. the youngeſt ſon of Doctor <hi>John Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> Phyſician to <hi>Prince Henry,</hi> and from him had the honour at the font to receive his Chriſtian name. Being yet in his long coats, he was ſent to <hi>Eton School;</hi> and at thirteen years old, to <hi>Magd. Coll.</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Being to proceed Maſter of Arts, he was made <hi>Reader</hi> of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy Lecture there. <hi>An.</hi> 1629, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing twenty four years of age, he entred into holy <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. An.</hi> 1633, having preached at Court for Dr. <hi>Frewen,</hi> he was preferred by the Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi> to the Rectory of <hi>Penſehurſt.</hi>*</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the diſcharge of his <hi>Miniſterial function</hi> (at <hi>Penſehurſt)</hi> he ſatisfyed not himſelf in dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and conſtant <hi>preaching</hi> only (a performance
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:187791:56"/> wherein ſome of late have phanſied all Religion to conſiſt) but much more conceived himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to the offering up the ſolemn <hi>dayly Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> for his people, adminiſtring the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> relieving the <hi>poor,</hi> keeping <hi>Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> reconciling of <hi>Differences</hi> amongſt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, viſiting the <hi>ſick,</hi> catechiſing of the <hi>Youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the firſt of theſe, his <hi>Preaching,</hi> 'twas not at the rate of the Times, an unpremeditated, undigeſted effuſion of ſhallow and crude conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions; but a rational and juſt diſcourſe, that was to teach the <hi>Prieſt</hi> as well as the <hi>Lay-hearer.</hi> His <hi>Method</hi> was (which likewiſe he recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his Friends) after every Sermon to reſolve upon the enſuing Subject; that being done, to purſue the courſe of ſtudy which he was then in hand with, reſerving the cloſe of the week for the proviſion for the next <hi>Lords-day.</hi> Whereby not only a conſtant <hi>progreſſe</hi> was made in Science, but <hi>materials</hi> unawares were gaind unto the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate future work: <hi>for,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>be the Subject treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of never ſo diſtant, ſomewhat will infallibly fall in conducible unto the preſent purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The offices of <hi>Prayer</hi> he had in his Church, not only upon the Sundays or Feſtivals and their Eves, as alſo <hi>Wedneſdayes</hi> and <hi>Fridayes,</hi> according to the appointment of the <hi>Rubrick</hi> (which ſtrict duty and miniſtration, when 'tis examined to the bottome, will prove the greateſt objection againſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:187791:56"/> the <hi>Liturgy)</hi> but <hi>every day</hi> in the week, and twice on Saturdays and Holy-day Eves: For his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance wherein he kept a <hi>Curate,</hi> and allow'd him a comfortable Salary. And at thoſe Devotions he took order that his <hi>Family</hi> ſhould give diligent and exemplary attendance: which was the eaſilier perform'd, it being guided by his <hi>Mother,</hi> a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>antient virtue,</hi> and one to whom he paid a more then filial obedience.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to the <hi>Adminiſtration of the Sacrament,</hi> he reduced it to an Imitation, though a diſtant one, of <hi>Primitive frequency,</hi> to once a month, and therewith its anciently inſeparable Appendant, the <hi>Offertory:</hi> wherein his <hi>Inſtruction</hi> and happily inſinuating <hi>Example</hi> ſo far prevail'd that there was thenceforth little need of ever making any <hi>taxe</hi> for the <hi>poor.</hi> Nay (if the report of a ſober perſon born and bred up in that Pariſh be to be believ'd) in ſhort time a ſtock was rais'd to be alwayes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the <hi>apprentiſing</hi> of young Children, whoſe Parents condition made the proviſion for them an equal Charity to both the Child and Parent. And after this there yet remain'd a ſuperpluſage for the aſſiſtance of the neighbour Pariſhes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For the <hi>Relief of the poor,</hi> beſides the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd expedient (wherein others were ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers with him) unto his private Charity, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating the Tenth of all Receits, and the daily Almes given at the door, he conſtantly ſet apart
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:187791:57"/> over and above, <hi>every week,</hi> a certain rate in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Yet farther, an other <hi>Art of Charity</hi> he had, the <hi>ſelling Corn</hi> to his poor Neighbours at a rate below the Market-price: which, (though, as he ſaid, he had reaſon to do, gaining thereby the charge of portage) was a great benefit to them, who, beſides the abatement of price and (poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) forbearance, ſaved thereby a days work.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He that was thus liberal to the neceſſitous poor, was no leſſe <hi>hoſpitable</hi> to thoſe of better quality: and as at other times he frequently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited his Neighbours to his Table, ſo more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially on Sundayes, which ſeldome paſt at any time without bringing ſome of them his gueſts: but here beyond the weekly treatments, the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtmas Feſtival</hi> had a peculiar allowance to ſupport it. He knew well how much the <hi>Application</hi> at the Table inforc'd the <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the Pulpit, and how ſubſervient the endearing of his <hi>Perſon</hi> was to the recommending his <hi>instructions,</hi> how far upon theſe motives our <hi>Saviour</hi> thought fit to eat with Publicans and Sinners, and how effectual the <hi>loaves</hi> were to the procuring of Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="7">7. As by publick admonition he moſt diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtill'd that great fundamental doctrin of <hi>Peace and Love,</hi> ſo did he likewiſe in his private addreſſe and converſation, being never at peace in himſelf till he had procur'd it among his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; wherein God ſo bleſt him, that he not
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:187791:57"/> only attain'd his purpoſe of uniting diſtant parties unto <hi>each other,</hi> but, contrary to the uſual fate of reconcilers, gain'd them to <hi>himſelf:</hi> there having been no perſon of his function any where better beloved then he when <hi>preſent,</hi> or lamented more when <hi>abſent,</hi> by his flock. Of which tender and very filial Affection, in ſtead of more, we may take two inſtances: the one, that he being driven away, and his <hi>books</hi> plunder'd, one of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours bought them in his behalf, and preſerved them till the end of the War: the other, that during his abode at <hi>Penſehurſt</hi> he never had any vexatious <hi>Law-diſpute</hi> about his dues, but had his <hi>Tithes</hi> fully paid, and not of the moſt refuſe parts, but generally the <hi>very beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Though he judged the time of <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> an improper ſeaſon for the great work of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet he eſteemed it a moſt uſefull <hi>Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> the voice of God himſelf exhorting to it: and therefore not only when deſir'd made his <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits</hi> to all ſuch as ſtood in need of thoſe his chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but prevented their requeſts by early and frequent coming to them. And this he was ſo carefull of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that after his remove from <hi>Penſehurſt,</hi> being at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and hearing of the Sickneſſe of one of his Pariſhioners, he from thence <hi>ſent</hi> to him thoſe Inſtructions which he judged uſefull in that Exigent, and which he could not give at nearer diſtance.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:187791:58"/> 9. For the Inſtitution of <hi>Youth</hi> in the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of piety, his Cuſtome was, during the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeaſon of the year, to ſpend an hour before Evening prayer in <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> whereat the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and older ſort were wont to be preſent, and from whence (as he with comfort was uſed to ſay) they reaped <hi>more benefit</hi> then from his <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi> Where it may not be ſuperfluous to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that he introduced no new form of <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> but adher<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d to that of the <hi>Church,</hi> rendring it fully intelligible to the meaneſt capacities by his <hi>Explanations.</hi> (It may be uſefull withall to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, that if in thoſe times <hi>Catechetical Inſtitution</hi> were very ſeaſonable, 'twill now be much more; when <hi>Principles</hi> have been exchang'd for dreams of words and notions.) Beſides all this, that there might be no imaginable aſſiſtance wanting, he took care for the providing an able <hi>School-maſter</hi> in the Pariſh, which he continued during the whole time of his abode.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And as he thus laboured in the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> building up of Souls, he was not negligent of the <hi>material</hi> Fabrick committed to his truſt: but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair'd with a very great expence (the annual charge of 100 <hi>l.)</hi> his <hi>Parſonage houſe;</hi> til from an incommodious ruin he had renderd it a fair and pleaſant dwelling, with the adherent conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of <hi>Gardens</hi> and <hi>Orchards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. While he was thus buſie on his Charge,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:187791:58"/> 
               <hi>&amp;c. But I earneſtly deſire the Reader to peruſe the whole ſtory of this excellent Divine excellently writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Venerable Dean. Only, I will take leave to adde here ſome of his Rules and Sayings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. He ſcarcely recommended any thing in his advices with that concern and vigor, as, <hi>To be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed alwaies with ſomewhat to do.</hi> This he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd as the beſt expedient both for innocence and pleaſure, aſſuring, <hi>That no burthen is more heavy, or temptation more dangerous, then to have Time ly on ones hand:</hi> adding, <hi>The idle mans brain is the Divels ſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. He profeſt, <hi>He had no ſuch way of enjoying any thing, as by reflection from the perſon whom he loved: ſo that his friends being happy was the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way to make him ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The principal thing he contracted for in Friendſhip was a free uſe of mutual <hi>Admonition:</hi> which he extended even to undecencies, ſaying, <hi>It was a poor deſign of Friendſhip to keep the Perſon he admitted to his breaſt only from being ſcandalous; as if the Phyſician ſhould endeavour only to ſecure his patient from the plague.</hi> And this he gave as a general rule, and enforc'd by his Example, <hi>Never to reprove in Anger,</hi> or the leaſt appearance of it.</p>
            <p n="15">15. He would ſay, <hi>He delighted to be loved, not reverenced;</hi> thinking that where there was much of the later, there could not be enough of the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:187791:59"/> former; ſomewhat of reſtraint and diſtance at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on the one, which was not well conſiſtent with the perfect freedom requiſite to the other.</p>
            <p n="16">16. To the performances of <hi>friendſhip</hi> he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed all mercenary returns, whereof he was ſo jealous, as hardly to leave place for gratitude, <hi>Love,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>was built upon the union and ſimilitude of minds, and not the bribery of gifts and benefits.</hi> So generous was he herein, that he has oft profeſt, <hi>He admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted retributions of good turns, yet not ſo much on any ſcore, as that his friend might have the pleaſure of being kind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. When any one had ſent him a ſlight pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>Apples</hi> or the like, his <hi>Reward</hi> would uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally much exceed the value; and he would be ſo well pleas'd to have ſuch an occaſion of giving to a ſervant, ſaying, <hi>Alas, poor Soul, I warrant he is glad of this little matter,</hi> that this ſeem'd a part of the ſenders courteſy.</p>
            <p n="18">18. He was us'd to ſay, <hi>That 'twas a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and unchriſtian thing to deſpiſe any one for his poverty.</hi> And, <hi>That 'twas one of the greateſt ſenſualities in the world, to Give:</hi> Upon which conſideration he often took occaſion to magnify the exceeding Indulgence of God, <hi>that had annext future rewards to that which was ſo amply its own Recompence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. He gave this for a Rule to thoſe of his friends that were of eſtate and quality, <hi>To treat</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:187791:59"/> 
               <hi>their poor Neighbours with ſuch a chearfulneſſe, that they may be glad to have met with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. To ſhew how high a value he put on the <hi>Souls</hi> of men, he often broke out into words of this effect, which had with them ſtill in the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very an extraordinary vehemence, <hi>O what a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thing, how rich a prize for the expence of a mans whole life were it, to be the inſtrument of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuing any one Soul!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. His Motto of inſtruction to young perſons was, <hi>Principiis obſta,</hi> and, <hi>Hoc age;</hi> to withſtand the overtures of ill, and be intent and ſerious in good: to which he joyn'd a third advice, <hi>To be furniſht with a Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. For ſerenity and calm of Mind, he layd this Rule before him, which prov'd of great uſe, <hi>Never to trouble himſelf with the foreſight of future events,</hi> being reſolv'd of our Saviours Maxime, <hi>Sufficient to the day is the evil thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. If he ſaw any perplext about the manage of their difficult affairs, he was wont to ask them, <hi>When they would begin to truſt God, or permit him to govern the World.</hi> And to himſelf and friends he was wont ſolemnly to give this mandate, <hi>Quod ſis eſſe velis, nihilque malis;</hi> in his Engliſh, <hi>to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nothing:</hi> Not only to be content or acquieſce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but be reſolv'd the preſent eſtate to be the very beſt that could be wiſht or phanſied.</p>
            <p n="22">22. He lookt upon the <hi>Kings return</hi> with pity
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:187791:60"/> and compaſſion, as bringing him to that uneaſy, if not inſuperable Task of ruling and reforming a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious people. <hi>It will be a bleſſing to his people, but unto him can not be ſo, but only on this ſcore, by having opportunities through glorious ſelf-denyals to do good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. When the <hi>Change</hi> approached, diſcourſing of occurrents, he broke forth into theſe words, <hi>I muſt confeſſe, I never ſaw that time in all my life, wherein I could ſo cheerfully ſay my</hi> Nunc dimittis, <hi>as now. Indeed I do dread proſperity, I do really dread it. For the little good I am now able to do, I can do it with deliberation and advice: but if it pleaſe God I ſhould live and be call'd to any higher office in the Church, I muſt then do many things in a hurry, and ſhall not have time to conſult with others, and I ſufficiently apprehend the danger of relying on my own judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. In his laſt ſickneſſe he comforted his ſad friends, ſaying, <hi>He ſhould leave them in God's hands, who could ſupply abundantly all the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance they could either expect or deſire from him; and who would ſo provide, that they ſhould not find his removal any loſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25. When in his ſharp agonies his friends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves to their extemporary ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he compos'd thoſe irregularities by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Let us call on God in the Voice of his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:187791:60"/> 26. At the Communion, hearing thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave ſinners,</hi> he pathetically rejoyn'd, <hi>Of whom I am chief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. To the good Lady of the houſe, who asked him, what he would chiefly commend to her, he briefly anſwer'd, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">28. A few minutes before his death, he breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out thoſe words which beſt became his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life, <hi>Lord make haſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. Apr.</hi> 25. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="biography">
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:187791:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:187791:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:187791:62"/>
            <head>X. Dr <hi>MILES SMITH. Biſhop of</hi> Gloc.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of the Preface before his Sermons, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Mr Jo.</hi> Stephens.</head>
            <p n="1">1. FOr the manner of his life and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant tenour of it, this I can affirm, that therein he ſhewed forth the fruits of the Spirit, ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>Love, Joy, Peace,</hi> &amp;c. Adde hereunto that ſincerity and godly pureneſſe that appeared in all his actions, ſtriving not ſo much to ſeem, as verily and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be a pattern of gracious deportment, and it may be ſaid of him, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> teſtifieth of <hi>Nathaniel, Behold an Iſraelite in whom was no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He alwaies ſhewed himſelf moſt ready to miniſter to the neceſſity of the indigent and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, having a tender touch even naturally that way. Yeerly <hi>penſions</hi> he allowed whileſt he lived,
<pb facs="tcp:187791:62"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:187791:63"/>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:187791:63"/> as his great charge would give him leave, to be diſtributed to the <hi>poor,</hi> as of the place where he was Biſhop, ſo in other places where he had means; beſides the dayly relief they of the City found at his gates. <hi>Exhibition</hi> of maintenance he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to divers <hi>poor Scholars</hi> in the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> whoſe parents were not able to ſuſtain that charge; and was ever forward in ſuccouring and relieving poor <hi>ſtrangers</hi> and <hi>travellers</hi> that came unto him. Whether his <hi>Alms</hi> were great or ſmall, they were alwaies mixed with alacrity and <hi>cheerfulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And as he was pitiful to the poor, ſo very charitable towards all, and apt to <hi>forgive</hi> wrongs and injuries done unto him, hardly to be digeſted in the ſtomach of a carnal man. The vertuous and religious he alwaies praiſed and incouraged, uſing inſtruction and rebuke to the contrary min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; not in the voice of <hi>thunder,</hi> in an over zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſtrain, but ſoft words of meekneſſe, the moſt likely, if not the only winning way. And in matter of <hi>doubt,</hi> the byas of his good inclination ſtil hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as every good mans ſhould do) towards the better ſenſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Naz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. His <hi>pietie</hi> muſt not be forgotten, his care of Gods true worſhip and zeal unto his houſe. It was his joy to ſee a company of well-devoted people to meet together to praiſe God; and to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:187791:64"/> that end, he did not onely continue a <hi>Lecture</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in his predeceſſors time) to be read in the <hi>Cathedral</hi> weekly on the <hi>Tueſday,</hi> by the graveſt Orthodox and <hi>Conformable</hi> Preachers within his Dioces, from the time of his entrance into that See, till he dyed; being full twelve years and upward: but did uſually preſent <hi>himſelf</hi> in the aſſembly at divine prayers and Sermons, both on the Lords Day and Lecture daies, if urgency of occaſions hindred not. And certainly there is nothing that ties the hearts of the people ſo cloſe unto their guides and governours, and maketh them ſo faithful each to other, as a joynt <hi>harmony</hi> and conſent therein. Hence he gained from men a reverend eſteem, he was honoured and beloved of all ſorts, and <hi>God,</hi> I doubt not, in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hath given him to find the fruit of his <hi>holineſſe</hi> in the fruition of his bleſſed preſence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Touching the things of this world, he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelf as though he looked not after them; never looking for any <hi>preferment</hi> that he had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was by Gods providence caſt upon him. Surely, the Biſhoprick of <hi>Gloc.</hi> was confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon him unſought for, unlooked for, at the ſuit of the <hi>Archb. of Cant.</hi> That of <hi>Naz.</hi> may be verified of him: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And now for his ſufficiency in <hi>learning,</hi> as therein I ſuppoſe he was inferiour to none,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:187791:64"/> either for knowledge in <hi>Divinity,</hi> or skill in the <hi>Eaſtern Tongues:</hi> So joyning to the <hi>height</hi> of his knowledge the <hi>Humility</hi> of his mind, for my part I muſt confeſs, that I never knew or heard of his match. Of his exactneſs in thoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, this may be a ſufficient teſtimony, that he was not only thought worthy by <hi>King James</hi> of bleſſed memory, to be called to the <hi>Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Bible,</hi> but was one of the <hi>twelve</hi> by whom it was reviſed; and at laſt it was referred to the final Examination of <hi>Biſhop Bilſon,</hi> and this our Biſhop: <hi>Viri eximii &amp; ab initio in toto hoc opere verſatiſſimi (Synod. Dord.)</hi> who happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded that worthy labour. The work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing finiſhed, <hi>Biſhop Smith</hi> was commanded to write a <hi>Preface,</hi> and ſo he did, in the name of all the <hi>Tranſlators</hi> (the ſame that is now extant in our <hi>Church-Bible)</hi> the <hi>Original</hi> whereof <hi>I</hi> have ſeen under his own hand.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Though he were ſo uſeful an inſtrument, ſo ſtrong a helper in the former work, as alſo the Sole-authour of this latter, the <hi>Preface:</hi> (a comely Gate to ſo rich and glorious a City:) yet could <hi>I</hi> never hear that he did at any time ſpeak of either, with any attribution to himſelf more then to the reſt. So that as the Sun, the nearer it cometh to the <hi>Zenith,</hi> the leſs ſhadow it cauſeth; ſo certainly the higher he mounted into the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Divine and Humane knowledge, the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:187791:65"/> lower and leſs he ſeemed to be in his own eyes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As <hi>Naz.</hi> ſpake of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. And now concerning the courſe of his <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> (wherein <hi>I</hi> would propoſe him as a <hi>Patern</hi> to be imitated by young ſtudents in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) he conſtantly applyed himſelf from his youth (as they that were then acquainted with him know) to the reading of <hi>antient Claſſical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours</hi> of the beſt note in their own languages: Wherewith, as with the <hi>Neoterick,</hi> he was plentiſully ſtored, and lufted after no worldly things, ſo much as books: <hi>Nullius rei praeterquam librorum avarus,</hi> was ſometime his own ſpeech merrily, but (as I perſwade my ſelf) truly, for there was ſcarcely a book (in ſo great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) to be found in his Library, eſpecially of the <hi>Antients,</hi> that he had not read over, <hi>a capite ad calcem,</hi> as hath been obſerved by thoſe that had the peruſal of them ſince his death.</p>
            <p n="9">9. He ran through the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and judiciouſly noted them in the margent, being ſitted for that purpoſe by the dextrous uſe of his pen, wherein he came not ſhort even of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ofeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ots themſelves in that faculty. The <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> alſo, ſo many as he had, with their <hi>Gloſſes</hi> and <hi>Commentaries,</hi> he read and uſed in their own <hi>id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om</hi> of ſpeech: and ſo converſant he was and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t in the <hi>Chaldee, Syriac,</hi> and <hi>Arabic,</hi> that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:187791:65"/> he made them as familiar to him almoſt, as his own native Tongue.</p>
            <p n="10">10. But for the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> this <hi>I</hi> can affirm from credible relation, that being upon a time ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and requeſted (whileſt he was a <hi>Reſidentiary</hi> in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Hereford: which ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was alſo honoured with his birth)</hi> by the then Dean of the ſame Church, upon ſpecial occaſion to read the firſt leſſon at evening prayer there, he yeilded thereunto; and having with him a little <hi>Hebrew Bible</hi> (the ſame <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe that he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards uſed to his death) of <hi>Plantins</hi> impreſſion <hi>ſine punctis;</hi> he delivered the Chapter there in the Engliſh Tongue plainly and fully, to that learned and judicious Auditory: (Far be from us any ſuſpicion of <hi>Oſtentation</hi> in him for that act, who never knew to boaſt of himſelf, or any thing that he had, or any thing that he did.)</p>
            <p n="11">11. Stories of all times he knew, and for his rich and accompliſht furniture in that ſtudy, had this <hi>Elogium</hi> given him by a grave and learned Biſhop, B. <hi>King,</hi> to be a very <hi>walking</hi> Library. And he was ſo well acquainted with the ſite of places, <hi>Topography,</hi> and obſerved ſo well the time when every thing of note was done in thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places, that he hath cauſed great Travellers and Scholers falling into diſcourſe with him, to depart away with admiration of his skill.</p>
            <div type="additions">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:187791:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Additions out of Mr.</hi> Priors <hi>Sermon at his Funeral.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="12">12. His merit in the new Tranſlation of the Bible, preferred him to this place of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church. For, with Baſilius Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, <hi>Non ex majoribus, ſed ex propria virtute no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitatem duxit:</hi> He ennobled himſelf with his own worth and virtue.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Two ſingular ornaments crowned him, which ſeldom meet in one man, <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Humility.</hi> On a time (and many ſuch I could tell you) a poor Miniſter ſending in to ſpeak with him, abruptly he brake off a moſt ſerious diſcourſe, ſaying, <hi>But the Miniſter muſt not ſtay, leſt we ſhould ſeem to take ſtate upon us.</hi> Therein imitating the great <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> being, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Nazianz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. When in his ſickneſs, one hoped for his recovery, he gave the <hi>anſwer</hi> that St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> gave to the Nobles of <hi>Milain,</hi> that deſired him to pray for life: <hi>Non ita inter vos vixi, ut pudeat ms vivere; nec timeo mori, quoniam dominum bonuns habemus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. Not many hours before his departure (for <hi>non obiit ſed abiit)</hi> I found him, as me ſeemed, victorious upon ſome conflict <hi>(Quis ſarctorum ſine certamine coronatur?)</hi> I drew near his bed, he
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:187791:66"/> reached for my hand and greezed it, ſaying, <hi>I know whom I have believed, and I am perſwaded, that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him againſt that day.</hi> This occaſioned ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing about <hi>relyance</hi> on God by Faith: <hi>Yea,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I had fainted, unleſs I had believed to ſee the goodneſs of the Lord in the land of the living.</hi> And again, <hi>The mercies of the Lord are from ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to generation, on them that fear him.</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy brought in thoughts of Chriſt: <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith he, in the words of that holy Martyr) <hi>none but Chriſt, none but Chriſt!</hi> Being told how preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly the Lord eſteemeth the death of ſuch: He replyed, <hi>Right dear, right dear in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of his Saints.</hi> Some prayers made for him upon his deſire, at concluſion, he ſaid: <hi>Amen, I thank God: Amen, enough: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I thank God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. When he was leaving this life he looked on his daughter, and on the reſt of his children in the chamber preſent, and ſaid: <hi>Chriſt bleſs you all.</hi> And like that old Patriarch, he moved himſelf upon the bed, and cried, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus help,</hi> and ſo Chriſt took him, and <hi>conclamatum eſt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ſoul is now at reſt: his Name is among the <hi>Worthies</hi> of our Church.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="grc" type="motto">
                  <body>
                     <head>His Motto.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob. A. S.</hi> 1624. <hi>aet ſupra</hi> 70.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:187791:67"/>
            <head>A Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>To fill up this void leaf, or rather to promote con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, which is partly the deſigne of theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials, I take leave to tranſlate hither out of the</hi> Oxford-book, <hi>very worthy to be Reprinted,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Letter of the Vice-Chancellour and others the Heads of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Cambridge, <hi>to the Vice-Chancellour and others of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Oxford, Octob. 7. 1603.</p>
            <p>E Latino.</p>
            <p>WHen ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, and indeed very late, there came unto us a report of the <hi>Petition</hi> for <hi>Reformation</hi> (forſooth) of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> offered to his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> (as is pretended) by a <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Miniſters:</hi> though we found in it <hi>nothing new,</hi> and what hath been <hi>anſwered</hi> heretofore a thouſand times; Yet, becauſe they boaſt of their number, that <hi>theſe Millenaries</hi> may know, if <hi>Saul</hi> hath his <hi>thouſand, David</hi> in this cauſe will never want his <hi>ten thouſand,</hi> we were deſirous (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the work was altogether unworthy of it) to provide an <hi>anſwer.</hi> Whilſt we were me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating thereof; there is brought unto our hands, that moſt <hi>Elegant</hi> anſwer of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Oxford,</hi> being a moſt <hi>rational</hi> and <hi>brief</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of all that had by thoſe men ſo labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly been framed and feigned: upon ſight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, nothing ſeemed to remain for us (whom in this <hi>beſt</hi> of cauſes, the zeal and induſtry of our
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:187791:67"/> 
               <hi>Brethren</hi> eaſily able to refute ſuch Adverſaries, had prevented) but this, to add unto the <hi>weight</hi> of their <hi>Arguments</hi> (becauſe thoſe men glory moſt in their multitudes) the <hi>number</hi> of our <hi>Suffrages.</hi> This we did formerly (as it were divining) both foreſee and provide for. For when, after the death of our Excellent <hi>Queen Elizabeth, alwaies the ſame</hi> and moſt conſtant (a ſingular and incomparable example in a woman) in this <hi>beſt</hi> of cauſes, <hi>thoſe men</hi> did not ſo much deplore the loſs of a moſt Religious <hi>Princeſs,</hi> and the caſe of <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf (if not dying with her, yet at leaſt in very great hazard) as meditate, and every day attempt <hi>Innovations</hi> againſt the new <hi>Kings</hi> approach: Our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> very opportunely judged her aid to be needful, and a <hi>decree</hi> to be made in a full and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Convocation: That, <hi>whoſoever ſhall in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Cambridge <hi>publickly oppoſe, in word or writing or any other way, the Doctrine or Diſcipline of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>or any part thereof, by Law eſtabliſhed; He ſhall be excluded from taking any degree, and be ſuſpended</hi> ipſo facto <hi>from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree he hath taken.</hi> Which decree, even by <hi>Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous</hi> conſent of the whole Houſe, voted and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded publickly, <hi>Jun.</hi> 9. 1603. we do now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to publiſh to the whole World, that all may be aſſured, what is the <hi>judgment,</hi> not of ſome <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niaſters</hi> in their corners and Conventicles, but of allmoſt all the <hi>Cantabrigians</hi> in open <hi>ſenate,</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:187791:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:187791:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:187791:69"/> concerning that <hi>Diſcipline</hi> which we have not forced on us, but freely received and entertained. Whoſe <hi>conſent</hi> ſo fraternally and ſweetly concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the <hi>Oxford-anſwer,</hi> with <hi>Scripture, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Councils,</hi> with the decrees of our <hi>Princes,</hi> our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Parliaments; Away</hi> with thoſe <hi>thouſand Miniſters,</hi> let them go and anſwer at <hi>thouſand Books</hi> of ours, already written and ſet forth for their ſatisfaction, before they do ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently obtrude their <hi>Crambe</hi> ſo often boiled, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo wiſe a <hi>King,</hi> and ſo excellently learned. Or if they would have <hi>Suffrages</hi> rather to be numbred then <hi>weighed,</hi> let the <hi>poor Fellows,</hi> forſaken of the Univerſities and Muſes, bethink themſelves, of how <hi>little account,</hi> what <hi>nothings</hi> they are.</p>
            <p>Thus we take our leave of our moſt dear Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hren in Chriſt; and, as we and our Vniverſity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng united to you, both by ſimilitude of <hi>ſtudies</hi> and <hi>manners,</hi> are moſt fitmly <hi>Yours;</hi> So we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you, alwaies to continue your love to <hi>Us.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Camb.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Oct.</hi> 7. 1603.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:187791:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
